[音乐播放]
[MUSIC PLAYING]
科尔顿·奥格登：嗨 晚上好
COLTON OGDEN: Hey, good evening.
欢迎来到GD50第四讲
Welcome to GD50 lecture four.
这是超级马里奥兄弟
This is Super Mario Bros.
然而 正如这里的幻灯片所示 我们是
As seen on the slides here, though, we're
而不是使用真正的超级马里奥兄弟精灵床单
not using the actual Super Mario Bros. sprite sheet.
这有点像敲竹杠
This is sort of like a rip off.
但我发现了一张非常棒的雪碧表
But I found a really awesome sprite sheet
所有的基本瓷砖 我们需要让这件事工作
that has all the basic tiles that we need to get this thing working.
在发行版中有一个链接 可以在哪里在线找到它
There's a link in the distro as to where you can find it online.
我玩得很开心
I had a lot of fun playing with it.
所以希望 如果你好奇 也许你
So hopefully, maybe if you're curious, you
可以用里面的一些精灵去做你自己的事情
can use some of the sprites in there to go off and do your own thing.
但超级马里奥兄弟--这堂课和作业的实际游戏
But Super Mario Bros.-- the actual game which this lecture and assignment are
基于--这是这里显示的游戏
based off of-- is the game shown here.
我想每个人都知道这是什么
I think everybody knows what it is.
这可能是有史以来最著名的比赛
It's probably the most famous game of all time.
但这款游戏是1985年问世的--
But this game came out in 1985--
在某种程度上给游戏行业带来了革命
sort of revolutionized the gaming industry.
正是这款游戏将游戏行业从崩溃中拯救出来
It was the game that brought the gaming industry from a crash
在70年代 由于许多糟糕的游戏制作政策
in the '70s thanks to a lot of poor game making policies
以及公司和低质量保证标准
and companies and low QA standards.
它基本上经历了70年代末80年代初的游戏崩盘
It basically took the gaming crash of the late '70s, early '80s
并将游戏真正带回了人们意识的前沿
and brought games really back to the forefront of people's consciousness.
这款游戏和像塞尔达传奇这样的游戏以及许多其他NES游戏
This and games like Legend of Zelda and a lot of other NES titles
使任天堂基本上成为视频游戏的霸主
made Nintendo basically the dominator of the video games
80年代和90年代的工业
industry in the '80s and '90s.
即使在今天 有了像《野性呼吸》这样的游戏
And even today, with games like Breath of the Wild,
他们仍在做自己的事
they're still doing their thing.
这是超级马里奥兄弟
This is Super Mario Bros.
这是一个2D平台
It's a 2D platformer.
这基本上意味着你控制着马里奥 他是一名水管工
And what this basically means is you control Mario, who's a plumber.
他走来走去 站在一边看着他
He goes around, walks sort of looking at him from the side.
他从左走到右
He walks left to right.
他能跳上跳下
He can jump up and down.
他受到重力的影响
He's affected by gravity.
他能打出盖帽
He can hit blocks.
他能扑向敌人
He can jump on enemies.
他可以顺着管道往下走 有很多层
He can go down pipes, and there's a bunch of levels.
在当时 这是一场相当复杂的游戏
It was, for its time, quite a complicated game,
它催生了无数的分支和盗版以及其他优质产品
and it spawned numerous offshoots and rip offs and other good quality
平台玩家
platformers.
当我们今天谈论《超级马里奥兄弟》时
While we talk about Super Mario Bros. today,
我们将要讨论的一些主题是平铺地图--
some of the topics we'll actually be talking about are tile maps--
所以我们可以用一系列的数字
so how we can take basically a series of numbers--
把ID拼起来变成游戏世界
tile IDs-- and turn that into a game world.
正如你在这里看到的 游戏被分成16乘16的方块
As you can see here, the game is broken up into blocks of 16 by 16 tiles.
你可以看到砖块和问号块
You can see the bricks and the question mark blocks,
管道甚至都是由简单的瓦片组成
and the pipes are even all composed of simple tiles.
它们映射到身份证
And they map to IDs.
当你有一个2D表格或数组 你只是把它全部覆盖起来
And when you take a 2D table or array and you just iterate over all of it
并在适当的x y
and render the appropriate tile at the appropriate x, y,
你会感觉自己存在于某个游戏世界中
you get the appearance of existing in some game world,
尽管它只是由一堆小方块组成
even though it's just composed of a bunch of tiny little blocks.
2D动画是我们将要讨论的内容
2D animation is something we'll talk about.
到目前为止 我们还没有真正做任何动画
So far, we haven't really done any animation
至少在性格方面是这样的
at all in terms of at least characters.
我们会和马里奥一起做的
We'll do that with Mario.
他会有我们版本的马里奥 外星人
He'll have-- our version of Mario, an alien--
当他移动的时候 他会有两帧动画
when he's moving, he'll have two frames of animation.
动画的画面--有点像一本翻页书
The frames of animation-- that's sort of like a flip book
如果你用过的话 你可以看到单独的图片
if you've ever used one, where you can see individual pictures.
当你快速地背靠背展示它们时
And when you display them rapidly back to back,
你会看到动画的外观
you get the appearance of animation.
我们会讨论的
We'll be talking about that.
程序化关卡生成--我们将把所有的关卡
Procedural level generation-- we'll be making all of our levels
随机生成
generate randomly.
所以每次我们从头开始玩这个游戏
So every time we play the game from the beginning,
一切都会完全不同
everything will be completely different.
我们不必硬编码一组有限的水平
We don't have to hard code a finite set of levels.
在我看来 一切都将是动态的 也是有趣的
Everything will be dynamic and also interesting, in my opinion.
我们会讨论一些平台物理学的基础知识
We'll talk about the basics of platformer physics
以及如何将其应用到游戏世界中
and how we can apply that to our game world
这里 因为我们只是使用一个瓷砖表
here, because we are just using a table of tiles,
每一个都有一个x y在游戏世界空间中被硬编码
each with an x, y that's hard coded in the game world space.
我们要做的就是拿马里奥的x y
All we have to really do is take an x, y of Mario, for example,
然后除以图块大小
and then just divide that by the tile size.
然后我们基本上得到了
And then we get basically what tile that is
在我们的阵列中 在世界的那个点
in our array at that point in the world.
因此可以很容易地进行任意的碰撞检测
And so it's really easy to do arbitrary collision detection based
关于你要去的方向 而不是迭代
on what direction you're going and not have to iterate over
你世界里的每一块瓷砖
every single tile in your world.
因为这只是一个简单的数学运算 就可以得到准确的切片
Because it's just a simple mathematical operation to get the exact tile
给出两个坐标 因为世界在一个固定的空间里
given two coordinates, since the world is in a fixed space.
我们将在我们的游戏中有一个小蜗牛
We'll have a little snail in our game that
四处走动 做几个随机的动画
walks around and does a couple of random animations
它会追逐玩家 就像是人工智能的一个基本入门
and will go after the player, sort of like a little basic intro to AI.
最后 我们将讨论通电和游戏对象之类的东西
And then lastly, we'll touch on things like power ups and game objects
以及我们可能如何影响马里奥并获得这些
and how we might be able to influence Mario and pick those up
诸如此类的事情
and that sort of thing.
所以 首先 我们来看一段演示
So first though, a demo.
所以如果有谁愿意上台
So if anybody is willing to come up on stage
要测试我的Mario实现 那将是非常棒的
to test out my implementation of Mario, that would be awesome.
詹姆斯?
James?
我要进入这里 所以我们应该都准备好了
I'm going to go ahead into here, so we should be all ready to go.
所以一旦你准备好了 继续并点击那里的返回
So as soon as you're ready, go ahead and hit Return there,
而且你应该启动并运行它
and you should be up and running.
所以作为随机水平的一部分--
So as a part of having random levels--
所以目前 我们有一个绿色外星人
so currently, we have a green alien.
在这种情况下 这些区块有一个随机的机会来产生宝石
The blocks have a random chance in this case to spawn a gem.
因此 一旦他们这样做了 你就可以拿起宝石了
And so once they do, you can pick the gem up.
要么他们有宝石 要么他们没有
Either they have a gem or they don't.
你可以拿起它 你会得到100分
You can pick it up, and you get 100 points.
正如我们所见 世界在某种程度上正在发生变化
As we can see, the world is sort of shifting
基于詹姆斯的化身在哪里 所以它跟踪角色
based on where James's avatar is, so it tracks the character.
我们对相机有了一些概念
We have some notion of a camera.
到目前为止 你在积木上越来越不走运了
You're getting unlucky with the blocks so far.
所以你可能会从空间中掉下来 所以你可能会想要避免这种情况
So you can fall down through the spaces, so you probably want to avoid that.
但如果你想演示一下如何做到这一点
But if you want to demonstrate doing it--
因此 在这种情况下 我们与它下面的两个街区相撞
so in that case, we collided with the two blocks below it.
右边的那个有宝石
The one on the right had the gem.
所以请继续往下倒 这样我们就可以演示了
So go ahead and just fall down so we can demonstrate.
因此 当我们摔倒时 我们会检测玩家是否
So when we fall down, we detect whether the player
低于世界极限 然后我们让他回来
has gone below the world limit, and then we start him back
在比赛开始的时候
at the beginning of the game.
你可以按Enter键 它应该会重生一个全新的世界
You can press Enter, it should regenerate a brand new world.
注意我们是如何在地面上随机打洞的
Notice how we have random holes in the ground.
我们有随机的瓷砖
We have random tiles.
我们为他们准备了随机的头衔
We have random toppers for them.
所有的区块都是随机的
All the blocks are random.
我们现在有蜗牛了
We have snails now.
他们在追逐詹姆斯
They're sort of chasing after James.
他可以跳到它们上面
He can jump on top of them.
这里有很多移动的小棋子 但也有很多
There's a lot of little moving pieces here, but a lot of them
实际上非常简单
are actually pretty simple.
我很快就会向你们展示
And I'll show you very shortly.
詹姆斯：我应该停下来吗？
JAMES: Should I stop?
科尔顿·奥格登：是的 当然
COLTON OGDEN: Yeah, sure.
这将是一个很好的观点
That would be a great point.
所以谢谢你 詹姆斯
So thanks, James.
非常感激
Appreciate it.
目前 还没有水平结束的概念
Currently, there is no notion of a level ending.
这是这篇文章的一部分 实际上将
That's part of the piece that actually will
产生一个玩家可以与之交互的对象 只是重新触发
spawn an object that the player can interact with to just sort of retrigger
基本上是一个新的水平
a new level, basically.
但这个基本平台背后的整个引擎都在那里 而且都能正常工作
But the whole engine behind this basic platformer is there, and it all works.
所以我们的目标是在这里看到的
And so our goal is seen here.
我们在这堂课的目标是演示
Our goal in this lecture is to demonstrate
我们怎样才能让角色在屏幕上四处移动
how we can get things like a character that moves around on a screen,
还有一个摄像头可以跟踪他们的位置 还有随机化的瓷砖
and a camera that tracks their position, and tiles that are randomized.
也许地上有柱子 地上有洞
And maybe there are pillars in the ground, holes in the ground.
所有这一切 再一次--
All of this, again--
至少瓷砖--只是以数字的形式存储
at least the tiles-- are stored as just numbers.
所以我们真正需要做的就是对一系列数字进行转换
So all we really need to do is perform a transformation on a series of numbers.
也许1等于有一块瓷砖 0等于空白
Maybe 1 is equal to a tile being there, 0 is equal to empty space.
所以只要看看它 我们就会看到我们一列接一列地看
And so just by looking at it, we'll see we go column by column.
我们可以说 哦 也许有机会不会在Y方向上产生任何瓷砖
We can say, oh, maybe there's a chance to not spawn any tiles along the y
在这张世界地图的第x栏上
column on this x of the world map.
或者在这个特殊的y上 也许不是产卵到地面
Or on this particular y, maybe instead of spawning the ground level,
我们在它上面和下面繁殖一对 这样我们就得到了一根柱子
we spawn a couple above it and down so that we get a pillar
以此类推
and so on and so forth.
就是这些随机化的总和
And it's just this summation of these randomizations
相当于游戏级别的一个不错的小变化
equals a nice little variety of game levels.
所以我们首先要讨论的是什么是平铺地图
So the first thing we should talk about really is what a tile map is.
到目前为止 我提到的是你真的可以想到一张瓷砖地图
And what I've alluded to so far is you can really think of a tile map
作为有效的二维数组或数字表格
as being effectively a 2D array or a table of numbers.
它比这要复杂一点 这取决于它有多复杂
And it's a little more complicated than that depending on how complex
你的平台是这样的 因为有些数字等于实心的瓷砖
your platformer is, because some numbers are equal to tiles that are solid
或者不去
or not.
所以你应该能够检查瓷砖是否可碰撞
So you should be able to check whether a tile is collidable,
这意味着玩家或您要检查的任何实体
meaning that the player or whatever entity you want to check for
可能真的会与它相撞 或者
can actually collide with it or
不
Not.
因此 很明显 我们不想在空瓷砖上引发碰撞
So obviously, we don't want to trigger a collision on empty tiles.
我们希望球员能够在这些比赛中自由移动
We want the player to move freely through those.
但如果它们撞到墙上 或者重力在影响它们
But if they run up against a wall or if gravity is affecting them,
当它们击中它们下面或上面的瓷砖时 我们希望检测到碰撞
and they hit tiles below them or above them, we want to detect a collision
然后根据它们的移动方向阻止它们
and then stop them based on which direction they're moving.
根据你使用平台的复杂程度 也许
And depending on how complicated you get with your platformer, maybe
例如 你有动画瓷砖
you have animated tiles, for instance.
因此 如果对切片进行了动画处理 它将显示不同的动画帧
So if a tile's animated, it will display a different frame of animation
根据你使用的定时器
based on what timer you're on.
真的 天空是无限的
Really, the sky's the limit.
在本例中 我们将相当简单
In this case, we'll be fairly simple.
我们的瓷砖将主要是带有几个其他特征的数字 这些
Our tiles will mostly just be numbers with a couple of other traits, which
我们稍后会看到的
we'll see later on.
这只是一个非常简单的地图的例子--只是一张彩色的地图
And this is just an example here of a very simple map-- just a colored
背景资料
background.
我们有自己的角色 然后我们可以把所有这些瓷砖可视化
We have our character, and then we can sort of visualize all of those tiles
只是为了理论上的0或1
as being just for the sake of theory 0s or 1s.
Tables0--所以我将实际进入一点实现
So tiles0-- so I'll actually get into a little bit of implementation
下面是我们如何开始画一些非常简单的瓷砖
here as to how we can get drawing some very simple tiles.
所以 如果你在看发行版 以磁贴0
So if you're looking at the distro, in tiles0
将是我们从这里开始的地方
is going to be where we start off here.
我将继续运行磁贴图 这样我们就可以看到它是什么样子的
And I'm going to go ahead and run tiles0 so we can see what that looks like.
所以这就是瓷砖0
So this is just tiles0.
这是一个比我们刚才看到的简单得多的程序 但我们在这里所做的
It's a much simpler program than what we just saw, but all we're doing here
只是背景中的一种颜色 然后是瓷砖
is just a color in the background and then tiles.
走出大门 有谁知道第一步会是什么
Off the gate, anybody have any ideas as to what the first step would
如果我们想要实施这一点呢？
be if we wanted to implement this?
观众：只要把瓷砖放在一个圈里 画出来 然后有一个背景就可以了？
AUDIENCE: Just put the tiles in a loop, draw them, and then have a background?
科尔顿·奥格登：所以把瓷砖放在一个圈里 画出来
COLTON OGDEN: So put the tiles in a loop, draw them,
然后了解一下背景情况
and then have a background.
是
Yes.
因此 基本上 如果这是我们磁砖中的主要Lua
So basically, if this is main.lua in our tiles0,
我们首先需要一张瓷砖桌子来存放我们的--
first thing we're going to need is a tiles table to store our--
我们不会只存储纯平的数字
we're not going to be storing just flat numbers.
我们将存储一些小桌子 里面有号码和身份证
We'll be storing little mini tables that have a number in them and ID,
所以如果我们有一个2D表格 我们可以说tile.id
so we can say tile.ID if we have a 2D table.
在这里 我们有一张空桌子
Here, we have an empty table.
我们要把它填满
We're going to populate that.
如果我们要画我们的瓷砖 我们需要某种精灵
If we're going to draw our tiles, we are going to need a sprite of some kind.
我所做的就是在这里切下一小段
And what I did was I just chopped out a little segment here.
这就是tiles.png
So this is tiles.png.
从字面上看 它只是主精灵的一块瓷砖
It's just literally one tile from the main sprite
随发行版一起提供的床单
sheet that comes with the distro.
然后右边是透明的 所以我们可以抵消--
And then on the right side is just transparent so that we can offset--
可能瓷砖ID%1等于实心块 然后瓷砖ID%2等于空
maybe tile ID 1 is equal to solid block, and then tile ID 2 is equal to empty.
因此 如果我们回忆一下生成四边形 我们可以拆分一个精灵薄片
And so if we recall generate quads, we can split up a sprite sheet
分成我们想要的任何数量的四边形
into however many quads we want to.
假设这是16块高的瓷砖--
Let's say this is 16 tiles tall--
每一块瓷砖--然后整个东西是两块瓷砖宽
each tile-- and then the whole thing are two tiles wide.
所以它需要被分成两块独立的瓷砖
So it needs to be split into two separate tiles.
我们只需要生成四元组 然后我们就会有一张桌子
We'll just generate quads, and then we'll have, recall, a table.
该表的每个索引都将是
Each of the indexes of that table will be
映射到这些瓷砖之一的四边形
a quad that maps to one of these tiles.
所以1号是这块瓷砖 2号
So number 1 will be this tile here, number 2
将是这里的透明部分 然后
will be the transparent bit over here, and then
这就是我们的ID将如何有效地映射
that's how effectively our IDs are going to map
绘制到屏幕上的内容
into what gets drawn onto the screen.
ID是我们的四元表的索引
The ID is the index into our quad table.
回到图块0 我们这里只有一个地图的宽度和高度
So going back into tiles0, we have here just a map width and height.
我们只是想说生成一张20乘以20的地图
We're just going to say generate a map 20 by 20.
RBG--我们只是将其设置为随机的
RBG-- we're just going to make it random,
所以我们要用一种随机的颜色清除屏幕
so we're going to clear the screen with a random color.
然后这是Quads=GenerateQuads
And then this is the quads = GenerateQuads.
请注意 我们在这里传入了瓷砖大小
And notice that we're passing in tile size here.
这是一个很好的做法 只要让你的瓷砖大小恒定即可
It's good practice just to make your tile size a constant.
所以我们整堂课的瓷砖大小--
So our tile size in this entire lecture--
他们都将是16岁乘16岁
they're all going to be 16 by 16.
所以因为它们是对称的 所以我们只需要传入瓷砖大小
And so since they're symmetrical, we just pass in tile size TILE_SIZE.
然后这就是我们最终产生地图的地方--
And then here is where we actually end up spawning the map--
所以嵌套了for循环
so nested for loop.
Y表示贴图高度为1 x表示贴图宽度为1
y gets 1 to map height, x gets 1 to map width.
请记住 我们必须将一个空表插入到基表中
Remember, we have to insert a blank table into the base table that's
将作为我们当前的行
going to act as our current row.
然后在那一行中 我们将在Tiles y添加一个小号
And then in that row, we're going to add a small at tiles y,
因为y将在这里--我们当前的行和ID
because y is going to be up here-- our current row and ID.
所以我们在这里做的是 如果y小于5-
And so what we're doing here is if y is less than 5--
这意味着我们基本上只会为地面设置一个任意点
meaning we'll just set an arbitrary point for the ground, basically.
如果距离顶部少于5块 那么就让它成为天空
If it's less than 5 tiles from the top, then just make it the sky.
所以天空--在这里的24 25线--我们只是
And so sky-- up here on line 24, 25-- we just
设置两个磁贴ID 正如我之前所说的
set two tile IDs, as I said before.
天空是2 所以它将在床单的右侧
Sky is 2, so it's going to be on the right side of the sheet.
然后 地面就是一个
And then ground is one.
这将是工作表中生成的第一个四元组
It's going to be the very first quad generated in the sheet.
因此 如果y小于5 则该ID应等于sky否则
So if y is less than 5, that ID should be equal to sky else
它应该等于地面
it should be equal to ground.
因此 在这里 这就是它发挥作用的地方
And so down here is where that comes into play.
我们将用我们随机的颜色清除屏幕
We're going to clear the screen with our random color.
正如James所说 我们将迭代遍历循环
We're going to iterate over the loop, as James said.
我们要在瓦片y x处拿到瓷砖
We're going to get the tile at tiles y x,
然后我们只需在该瓷砖ID处绘制床单和四边形
and then we're just going to draw the sheet and the quads at that tiles ID.
然后回想一下 由于表是1索引的 而坐标是0索引的
And then recall, since tables are 1 indexed but coordinates are 0 indexed,
我们取x和y 减去1
we take the x and the y, subtract 1 from them,
然后我们只需将它们乘以瓷砖大小
and then we just multiply them by tile size.
它的效果是画出每一块瓷砖
And that has the effect of drawing each of those tiles
在他们各自的世界节点上 并使
at their respective point in the world and making
看起来好像我们有了这个世界--这堆砖
it seem as if we have this world-- this bunch of bricks
每次都有一个随机的背景
with a random background every time.
这并不是很有趣 但只是稍微多样化了一点
Which isn't all that interesting, but just a little bit more variety.
这就是它背后的最基本的要点
And so that's the very basic gist behind it.
我的意思是 这基本上和我们在第三场比赛中做的差不多
I mean, it's essentially almost the same thing as what we did in match three,
我们只是把每一个小块
where we just mapped the individual tiles that
分别在网格中以索引的方式在瓷砖板上按颜色和品种分类
were in the grid to indexes in the tile sheet based on the color and variety.
只是这次 他们会一直待在同一个地方
Only this time, they're always going to be in the exact same place,
所以我们不必担心它们的x和y
so we don't have to worry about whether their x and y are
不同于y和x坐标
different from their grid y and grid x.
我们不保留对这些的引用
We're not maintaining a reference to those.
这就是静态瓦片
And so that's static tiles.
有人对我们如何
Does anybody have any questions about how we just
在屏幕上绘制静态图块？
draw static tiles to the screen?
很基本的东西
Pretty basic stuff.
整个名称背后的侧滚动游戏
The whole name behind side scrolling game
就是方块的滚动是基于我们在游戏中的动作
is that the tiles scroll based on what we're doing in the game.
它可以是一个自动滚动 在这种情况下
It can be an auto scroller, in which case
也许你是一架飞机
maybe you're an airplane that's sort of going
通过自动滚动的关卡
through a level that's scrolling automatically,
而你在射击
and you're shooting things.
你并不能真正控制你要去哪里
And you're not really in control of where you go.
或者它可以像马里奥 你控制一个化身
Or it can be like Mario, where you control an avatar.
你可以四处走动 跳跃之类的
And you can walk around and jump and stuff,
摄像机会一直盯着你
and the camera will always be fixed on you.
所以滚动只是相对于你的角色的x和y的位置
And so the scrolling is just relative to where your character's x and y are.
所以我将给你们展示一个例子
So I'm going to show you guys an example of how we can
在我们的游戏中实现滚动
get scrolling implemented in our game.
为了做到这一点 我们真正要研究的函数--
And to do that, the function that we're really going to be looking--
在一个新的功能--
at a new function--
is love.graphics.translate（x y）.
is love.graphics.translate(x, y).
所以它所做的就是有效地将
And so what that does is effectively just translates
Love 2D的坐标系 这样每当我们画东西的时候
Love2D's coordinate system so that whenever we draw something,
它会自动移动x y
it gets automatically shifted by x, y.
这就产生了所有东西都被扭曲的效果
And so that has the effect of the everything being sort of skewed
基于我们传递的x y
based on the x, y that we pass it.
所以如果我们保持一个字符所在位置的引用
And so if we maintain a reference to where the character is,
我们可以改变屏幕上所有东西的位置
we can just shift where everything gets drawn on the screen.
这会让它看起来像是一个摄像头 但它不是
And that will have the effect of it being a camera, but it's not.
我们所做的只是移动坐标系
All we're doing is just shifting the coordinate system
基于一些偏移量--
based on some offset--
在这种情况下 玩家是有效的
x being in this case where the players is effectively.
观众：所以它改变了整个坐标系？
AUDIENCE: So it changes the whole coordinate system?
科尔顿·奥格登：的确如此
COLTON OGDEN: It does.
它按x和y移动坐标系中绘制的所有对象
It shifts everything in the coordinate system that you draw by the x and y.
所以这基本上会影响所呈现的内容
And so that will basically affect what's getting rendered
进入当时的活动窗口
into the active window at that time.
所以我要继续往下拉瓷砖1
So I'm going to go ahead and pull up tiles1 here
所以我们可以看看这是如何运作的
so we can see how this works.
让我继续并首先运行程序
Let me go ahead and first run the program.
因此 如果我们要进入发行版的磁砖1
So if we're going into tiles1 in the distro,
目前它看起来几乎一模一样
currently it looks almost identical.
但是如果我只按向左或向右 我就可以移动它
But I can move it if I just press left or right.
所以我们可以在这里看到 这是2D瓷砖阵列
And so we can see here, this is where the 2D array of tiles
在这里被切断
gets cut off here.
然后它也被切断了 因为我们只生成了一个20x20的级别
And then it also cuts off, because we're only generating a 20 by 20 level.
它的最右边也被切断了
It also gets cut off at the very right side as well.
这些是您通常会对用户隐藏的详细信息
And these are details you would normally hide from the user
只需将x夹在0和右侧之间
by just clamping the x between 0 and the right side
贴图的大小减去虚拟宽度
of the map minus VIRTUAL_WIDTH.
而这将会产生这样的效果 无论你何时到达这一点
And that will have the effect of whenever you get to this point,
它不会再让你向右转了 同样的事情也会发生在左边
it won't let you go right anymore, and same thing for the left side.
嗯 我们现在所做的--我们没有
Well, all we're doing right now-- we're not
完全是根据角色来做的
doing it based on the character at all.
我们只是使用键盘输入
We're just using keyboard input.
因此 让我们继续讨论磁砖1
So let's go ahead into tiles1.
所以我们要看的重要的事情是--
And so the important thing that we're going to look at is--
正如我刚才提到的 我们将调用love.graph
as I just alluded to, we're calling love.graphics.translate
在名为CameraScroll的某个值上
on some value called cameraScroll.
它必须是负值 因为如果我们向右移动
It has to be a negative value, because if we're moving to the right
在这上面还是在左边--
up here or to the left--
如果我们向左移动 摄像机卷轴基本上会减少
if we're moving to the left, camera scroll basically is going to decrement,
所以它会变得更少
so it's going to get less.
所以我们可以说 当我们在
So we can say the camera scroll when we're
如果我们从0开始 向左转将是0或更小
going left is going to be 0 or less if we're starting at 0,
否则它就会减少
or it's going to decrement.
如果我们按向右 摄像镜头应该会增加
If we press right, camera roll should increase.
如果我们想要向右移动或向左移动的外观
If we want the appearance of moving to the right or moving to the left,
实际上 你必须以相反的方向翻译
you actually have to translate by the opposite direction.
因为如果我们看这个 如果我们调用love.graph 转换为正的
Because if we look at this, and if we call love.graphics.translate positive,
所有这些都将向右移动
all of this is going to get moved to the right.
所以它看起来就像我们在向左移动
So it's going to have the appearance of us moving left.
如果我们把它向左平移负数
And if we translate it to the left by a negative amount,
它会有我们向右移动的样子
it's going to have the appearance of us moving right.
因此 如果我们的卷轴是正面的 并且我们想要向右移动
So if our scroll is positive and we want to move to the right,
我们实际上必须将其转换为负值
we actually have to translate by a negative amount.
这就是为什么我把它命名为Native Math.Floor
And so that's why I'm calling negative math.floor(cameraScroll).
有人知道为什么我们要在摄像机上叫Math.Floor吗？
Does anybody know why we're calling math.floor on cameraScroll
而不是简单地调用底片相机滚动？
instead of just calling negative camera scroll?
有人记得Math.Floor是做什么的吗？
Does anybody remember what math.floor does?
所以数学 地板将返回--
So math.floor will return the--
它基本上会将数字向下截断到最小整数
it'll basically truncate the number down to the lowest integer.
它基本上会去掉浮点值
It will basically take off the floating point value.
因为我们正在渲染到虚拟分辨率
Because we're rendering to a virtual resolution
有了推力 如果我们基本上将平移偏移一小部分
with push, if we basically offset the translation by a fractional amount,
你会得到手工艺品
you'll get artifacting.
因为它夺走了你的窗户 只是冷凝
Because it's taking your window and just condensing
你的图像放到虚拟画布上 你会得到奇怪的模糊之类的东西
your image onto a virtual canvas, you'll get weird blur and stuff like that.
所以当你画一些东西的时候 你有一个分数
So whenever you draw something and you have a fractional number for something,
你把它画到一张被放大的虚拟画布上
and you're drawing it to a virtual canvas that's been magnified
或者它正在被浓缩 只要确保数学 平铺它
or it's being condensed, just make sure to math.floor it
所以你不会得到任何奇怪的模糊伪装
so you don't get any weird blur artifacting.
如果你把它拿出来试一试 或者即使是在发行版中
If you take this out and experiment around, or even if in the distro
你把它从球员的位置上拿出来 你就会看到球员
you take it out of the player's position, you'll see the player
会得到奇怪的模糊的人工制品之类的东西
will get weird blurry artifacting and stuff like that.
这就是为什么它在那里 如果你好奇的话
So that's why that's there, in case you're curious.
所以我们在这里所做的一切--我们只是想说
And so all we're doing here-- we're just saying
如果等于左 则向左滚动摄像机 向右滚动
if it's equal to left, scroll the camera left, scroll it right,
或者基本上减少我们的相机滚动 然后增加或相机滚动
or basically decrement our camera scroll and then increment or camera scroll.
然后在这里使用负面的版本
And then just use the negative version of that here.
您也可以将相机滚动指定为正数
You could also just assign camera scroll equal to positive
当你向左移动 当你向右移动时
when you move left and negative when you move right,
然后你可以在这里给它正常的相机卷轴
and then you could give it the regular camera scroll here.
但就这一部分而言 这是一种精神上的颠覆
But it's sort of mentally flipped in terms of this part.
所以当我们按向左的时候 我决定在这里减少它
So I just made the decision to decrement it here when we're pressing left,
因为当我们按向右的时候 我们在x轴上做得更少 然后在x轴上做得更多
because we're going less on the x and then more on the x when we press right.
这有意义吗？
Does this make sense?
有谁有问题吗？
Anybody have question?
观众：我有一个问题
AUDIENCE: I have a question.
在JavaScript中有没有相应的函数
Is there a corresponding function in JavaScript
而在像这样的其他语言中 你可以移动整个坐标吗？
and in other languages like this where you can shift a whole coordinate?
Colton Ogden：在JavaScript中有类似的函数吗
COLTON OGDEN: Is there an equivalent function in JavaScript
在那里你可以移动整个坐标系？
where you can shift the whole coordinate system?
可能不是在基本的JavaScript中
Not in base JavaScript, probably.
我对css不是很熟悉
I'm not too familiar with CSS.
可能有一个css函数可以做到这一点
There might be a CSS function that does it.
在许多2D游戏引擎中 是的 我会说
In a lot of 2D game engines, yes, I would say.
许多实际的2D游戏引擎都会有一个摄像头对象 它
And a lot of actual 2D game engines will have a camera object, which
这在某种程度上概括了这一行为
sort of encapsulates this behavior.
Love2D没有摄像头 所以这是排序
Love2D doesn't have a camera, so this is sort
我们为什么要这样做--是因为这是一种较低级别的游戏
of why we're doing this-- is because it's kind of a lower level game
框架 Love2D
framework, Love2D.
它不会给你带来那么多东西
It doesn't really give you as many things
就在门口 这使得它非常适合教授这些概念
right out the gate, which makes it great for teaching these concepts.
但更强大的解决方案 如Unity或Phaser
But a more robust solution like Unity or Phaser
或许多其他游戏框架 它们将只有一个摄像头对象
or a lot of other game frameworks is that they'll just have a camera object.
你只要给它你的x 然后你就移动它
And you just basically give that your x, and then you just move that.
你基本上是这样说的 以跟踪玩家--
You basically tell that to track the player--
比如camera.trackPlayer或trackEntityPlayer--
like camera.trackPlayer or trackEntityPlayer--
这也会产生同样的效果
and that'll have the same effect.
它稍微抽象了一点
It's a little bit more abstract.
这是一个比我们正在做的更高的水平
It's a higher level than what we're doing,
但这背后的原理是一样的
but it's the same exact principle underlying.
那么 关于这是如何运作的 还有其他问题吗？
So any other questions as to how this works?
好的 太酷了
All right, cool.
这就是我们正在做的所有事情
So that's all we're effectively doing.
我们只是得到一个相机卷轴 递减和递增它
We're just getting a camera scroll, decrementing it and incrementing it.
然后每一帧 我们都在翻译
And then just every frame, we're translating everything
在我们画完所有的画之前
before we draw everything.
你必须在画之前做平移 因为你做的每一件事
You have to do the translation before you draw, because everything that you
在平移受新坐标系更改影响后绘制
draw after the translation gets affected by the new coordinate system change.
这就是滚动
So that's scrolling.
让我们真正开始讨论如何画一个人--一个化身--
Let's get to actually talking about drawing a person-- an avatar--
不仅仅是一套瓷砖 因为这是游戏的核心
more than just a set of tiles, since that's what the game revolves around.
如果我们看一下Character 0 这将是我们这里的第一个示例
If we look at character0, this would be our first example here.
这只是一个非常简单的例子--
This is just going to be a very simple example--
字符0
charactr0.
你们可能已经知道这是怎么回事了
You guys probably know how this works already.
我们所做的只是在屏幕上画一个精灵--
All we're doing is just drawing a sprite to the screen--
所以就去爱吧 图画
so just love.graphics.draw.
我们从一块瓷砖上拿到了四边形
We're getting quads from a tile sheet.
我相信它就在幻灯片里
I believe it's in the slides.
实际的床单在这里
The actual sheet is here.
所以我们有一个小家伙--
So we have this little guy--
几帧动画
several frames of animation.
它有16个宽 20个高 我们只有一个四边形
It's 16 wide, 20 tall, and we just take a quad.
我们先把它分成四个部分
We split it up into quads first.
所以我们知道它是16×20高的 所以我们只生成四边形
So we know that it's 16 wide by 20 tall, so we just generate quads
在这张图上 16岁和20岁
on this image by 16 and 20.
在这个例子中 我们所做的就是
And then in this example, all we're doing
取下第一帧 也就是1次方 然后画出来
is taking the first frame, which is quads1, and just drawing that.
正如你在这里看到的 我们有一堆不同的东西
As you can see here, we have a bunch of different things.
我们有一种蹲着的状态 我们会
We have like a crouching state, and we'll
稍后我们将了解更多有关动画的内容
get to more about animations in a little bit.
但在这里 我们让他爬上了梯子
But here, we have him climbing up a ladder.
但你可以看到所有这些不同的框架
But you can see all these different frames.
我们将向您展示如何背靠背播放它们
We'll end up showing how you can play them back to back
并得到不同的动画
and get different animations.
但为了这个基本的例子 我们所做的一切
But for the sake of this basic example, all we're doing
只是渲染了第一帧
is just rendering the very first frame.
我们可以看到--
And we can see that--
让我确保我在正确的文件中 我是--
let me make sure I'm in the right file, which I am--
我们在第43行和第44行得到了角色表
we are getting the character sheet here on line 43 and 44.
然后我们必须给他一个X 所以CharacterX Charactery
And then we have to give him an x, So characterX, characterY.
在这种情况下 我们只是将他设置在7号瓷砖之上
In this case, we're just setting him above tile 7,
所以我们用7减去1乘以Tile_Size 因为切片是1索引的
so we do 7 minus 1 times TILE_SIZE because tiles are 1 indexed
但是坐标是0索引的
but coordinates are 0 indexed.
然后我们只需减去高度 他就会
And then we just subtract the height so that he's
就在瓷砖的上方 而不是瓷砖的右边
right above the tile instead of right at the tile.
然后在这里 我们做一个爱 画 画
And then down here, we do a love.graphics.draw
就像我之前说的 就是角色Quads1
on, as I said before, just characterQuads 1.
这只是一个非常基本的硬编码示例
Just a very basic hard coded example.
对于这是如何工作的 有什么问题吗？
Any questions at all as to how this works?
现在让我们假设我们想让他移动
So now let's say we want him to move.
我们需要什么？
What do we need?
如果我们只是想让他搬走 下一步该怎么办？
What's the next step if we just wanted him to move?
观众：给他一个x和y？
AUDIENCE: Give him an x and y?
科尔顿·奥格登：是的 给他一个x和y
COLTON OGDEN: Yes, give him an x and y.
所以是的 所以他已经有了x和y
So yes, so he does have an x and y already.
所以如果你看--我穿对了吗？
So if you look at-- am I in the right one?
所以如果你转到Character0 这仍然是Character0
So if you go to character0, this is character0 still.
我们已经给了他一个x和y 但还需要再走一步
We have given him an x and y already, but there needs to be another step.
另一个步骤涉及到什么？
What's the other step involved?
因此 如果我们想要移动 我们需要检查键盘输入
So if we wanted to move, we need to check for keyboard input.
然后我们需要取他的X--
And then we need to take his x--
我们现在只需要让他在x轴上移动
we're just going to move him on the x-axis for now.
我们基本上需要把他的性格变量X放在这里
We basically need to take his characterX variable up here,
我们需要修改这一点
and we need to modify that.
我们基本上可以做我们在Love这里所做的相同的事情
We can basically do the same thing that we did down here in love.update.
在此之前 它是在坐标系中--
Previously, it was on the coordinate system--
Love.graph ics.翻译
love.graphics.translate.
我们修改了相机卷轴
We modified the camera scroll.
我们将其设置为滚动速度乘以增量时间
We set that equal to scroll speed times delta time.
我们把它减去或相加
We subtracted or added it.
在这种情况下 我们要做的是有一个新的常量 称为
In this case, what we're doing is we have a new constant called
CHARACTER_MOVE_SPEED 我们正在执行完全相同的操作
CHARACTER_MOVE_SPEED, and we're just doing that exact same operation
但用的是Character X 而不是CameraScroll
but on characterX instead of cameraScroll.
因此 最终的结果是我们有了这个角色
So the end result of that is that we have the character here.
然后我们可以向左或向右移动他 他就会离开屏幕
And then we can move him left or right, and he go off screen.
现在 有几件事是错的
Now, there's a couple of things wrong.
怎么了？
What's wrong?
现在的场景有哪些地方出了问题？
What are some of the things that are wrong with the scene right now?
观众：镜头应该和他一起移动
AUDIENCE: The camera should move with him.
科尔顿·奥格登：相机应该和他们一起移动
COLTON OGDEN: Camera should move with them.
观众：没有动画
AUDIENCE: No animation.
科尔顿·奥格登：没有动画
COLTON OGDEN: Does not have animation.
这可能是两个真正的错误
Those are probably the two real things that are wrong.
所以摄像头不会跟踪他 这很重要
So camera does not track him, which is an important thing.
显然 我们希望能够保持对我们角色的引用
Obviously, we want to be able to maintain a reference to our character,
除非我们在屏幕的左边
unless we're at the left edge of the screen.
如果我们在屏幕的左边缘 这实际上是可以的
If we're at the left edge of the screen, this is actually OK.
这是分配的一部分--我们夹住x射线
And that's part of the distro-- is we clamp the x so
它不会超过左边
that it doesn't go past the left edge.
但是如果我们超出了中间 而不是屏幕的右边
But if we're beyond the middle and not to the right edge of the screen,
它应该和他一起运动 反之亦然
it should be moving along with him and vice versa.
然后他需要动画 所以他的精灵
And then he needs to animate, so his sprite
需要每隔一定的秒数改变一次是否在移动
needs to change every certain number of seconds whether he's moving.
只有在他移动的时候才能看到 对吧？
And it has to be only when he's moving, right?
如果他站着不动 你可以有一个空闲的动画
If he's standing still, you can have an idle animation.
有些角色会用脚敲 做这样的事情
Some characters will tap their foot and do stuff like that.
但为了这个例子 我们希望他
But let's say for the sake of this example we want him just
在他空闲的时候站着不动
to stand still when he's idle.
我们希望他在移动的时候有一个真实的动画
And we want him to have an actual animation when he's moving.
我们得处理好这两件事
We need to take care of these two pieces--
如果算上空闲的动画部分的话 有三块
three pieces if you count the idle animation part.
让我们进入角色2 处理第一部分
So let's go into character2 and take care of the first part, which
正在追踪他
is tracking him.
让我们进入角色2
So let me go into character2.
我们先运行一下看看是什么样的
Let's run it first so we can see what it looks like.
所以现在摄像头基本上是固定在播放器上的
So now the camera is basically affixed to the player.
在这个例子中 我们不考虑左边缘的问题
In this example, we don't take care of the left edge issue.
在发行版中 这是固定的
In the distro, that's fixed.
但是我们有基本的侧滚动机制--拿一个角色
But we have the basic side scrolling mechanic-- take a character,
追随她.
follow him.
你觉得我们是怎么做到的？
How do you think that we're accomplishing this?
是的
Yes.
观众：根据人物X翻译图画？
AUDIENCE: Translate the drawing against the characterX?
科尔顿·奥格登：是的 完全正确
COLTON OGDEN: Yes, exactly.
它不可能是X这个字符
And it can't be exactly the characterX though,
因为如果是的话 那么这个字符应该在左边 对吧？
because if it is, then the character is going to be on the left edge, right?
所以我们需要偏移我们平移的x
So we need to offset our x that we translate by.
我们需要基本上平移他的x减去一半的屏幕空间
We need to basically translate by his x minus half the screen space
加上字符宽度的一半
plus half the character width.
这将产生翻译它的效果 但始终保持
And that will have the effect of translating it but always keeping
如果这有道理的话 那就是偏离播放器半个屏幕宽度
that offset half a screen width away from the player, if that makes sense.
所以我们所做的是在角色中--这是角色2 对吧--
And so what we're doing is in character-- this is character2, right--
特征2 我们仍然在做我们曾经做过的事情
character2, we're still doing the same thing we did.
实际上 那是错误的文件
Actually, that's the wrong file.
我们在这里修改Character X
We are modifying characterX here.
所以我们之前做了同样的事情--
So same thing we did before--
将移动速度乘以增量时间 然后进行加法或减法
multiply the move speed by delta time and either add or subtract it
如果我们按向左或向右
if we're pressing left or right.
而且 在这里--重新引入相机卷轴
But also, here-- reintroducing camera scroll.
我们将其设置为 就像我说的 Character X减去虚拟宽度除以
And we're setting it to, like I said, characterX minus VIRTUAL_WIDTH divided
2 半个屏幕 然后正偏移量
by 2, half the screen, and then positive offset
他的宽度除以2 所以他正好在中间
of his width divided by 2 so that he's perfectly right in the center.
因为请记住 字符的坐标
Because remember, characters' coordinates
被放在他们的左边 而不是他们的中间
are set by their left, not their center.
然后我们只是做我们以前做过的事情
And then we just do what we did before.
我们根据CameraScroll对场景进行翻译
We translate the scene based on cameraScroll,
我们用Math.Floor将他呈现在CharacterX Charactery上
and we render him at characterX characterY using math.floor
以防止他在我们的世界空间中处于一个分割点
to prevent him from being at a fractional point in our world space
然后它变得模糊和做作
and then it being blurry and artifacted.
这就是我们如何跟踪角色的某种程度上的问题
And that's sort of it in terms of how we can get tracking over character.
如果你想沿着y轴追踪
And if you wanted to track along the y-axis,
你也可以做同样的事情
you could do the exact same thing.
维护相机滚动X和摄像机滚动Y--
Maintain a cameraScroll x and a cameraScroll y--
所以要把它们分开
so keep them separated.
然后你就可以在这里翻译了
And then you would just translate here.
所以我们传入0 因为我们不想
So we're passing in 0, because we don't want
必须沿y轴跟踪
to track along the y-axis necessarily.
但您需要做的就是传递您的y CameraScroll
But all you would need to do is pass in your y cameraScroll.
然后你可以根据性格来做
And then you could do it based on characterY
不管它们是否在地面上
and whether or not they're above the ground
或者越过天空中的某个点
or past a certain point in the sky.
那么 对于这里的摄像头跟踪系统是如何工作的 有什么问题吗？
So any questions at all as to how the camera tracking is working here?
好的
All right.
所以我们解决了一个问题 那就是缺乏跟踪
So we took care of one issue, which was the lack of tracking.
但还有一个问题 那就是他没有动画
But there was one other issue, which was he's not animated.
他所做的就是像M.C.哈默那样移动--
All he's doing is just moving sort of like M.C. Hammer--
或者是M.C.Usher？
or is it M.C. Usher?
M.C.哈默？
M.C. Hammer?
我忘了
I forget.
他就是这么做的
He's doing that.
他什么都没做
He's not doing anything.
我们需要让他动起来 这样他看起来就像有生命一样
We need to actually animate him so that he looks like he has some life to him
而且你还可以重要地区别于
and that you can also differentiate importantly
在两个不同的状态之间
between two separate states.
他可以无所事事 不动 也可以动起来
He can be idle, he's not moving, and he can be moving.
所以我们应该有某种视觉反馈
So we should have some sort of visual feedback
关于目前正在发生的事情
as to what's currently going on.
因此 有谁知道我们如何着手实施
So anybody know how we can go about implementing
为我们的角色制作动画片？
an animation for our character?
我们需要哪些零件？
What are the pieces that we'll need?
观众：我想如果他走对了 那么
AUDIENCE: I guess if he's moving right, then
调用一个函数和一个渲染来查看一些图像？
call a function and a render that looks through some images?
科尔顿·奥格登：是的
COLTON OGDEN: Yes.
所以如果他向右移动 那么就有一个功能
So if he's moving right, then have a function
这就像是在一些图像中循环
that sort of loops through some images.
这实际上就是我们将要做的事情
That is effectively what we will be doing.
我们有一个叫动画的课程 我已经在这里介绍过了
We have a class called Animation, which I've introduced here.
它所做的基本上就是跟踪--你
And all it basically does is keep track of-- you
将其传递到一个表中 该表包含工作表的框架
pass it in a table, which has the frames of the sheet
您想要设置动画的对象
that you want to animate over.
所以我们可以直接进去--
So we can just pass in--
让我们继续前进 看看这里
let's go ahead and take a look here.
我之前参考了这张幻灯片 但所有这些
And I referenced the slide earlier, but all of these
有1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 10--不管有多少
are 1, 2, 3, 4, 5, 6, 7, 8, 9, 10-- however many there are,
你只要进入动画即可
you just pass into the animation.
假设他在梯子上
Let's say he's on a ladder.
假设这是1、2、3、4、5、6和7
So let's say this is 1, 2, 3, 4, 5, 6, and 7.
你说 帧将是6和7
You say, the frames are going to be 6 and 7,
所以它们会从左到右循环 从后面开始
so those will just loop left to right, starting back
在开始的时候 当它结束的时候 然后你给它一个间隔
at the beginning when it's finished And then you give it an interval.
比方说 我希望动画以秒为单位这么快地发生
So say I want the animation to happen this fast in terms of seconds,
所以我希望它可能每0.2秒发生一次
so I want it that maybe happened every 0.2 seconds.
因此 这将产生每0.2秒的影响
And so that will have the effect of every 0.2 seconds,
它会记录一个计时器
it'll keep track of a timer.
那么我们已经超过0.2秒了吗？
So have we gone over 0.2 seconds?
从0开始 然后每次都加上增量时间
Start at 0 and then add delta time to it every time.
如果有 则增加当前动画的帧
If we have, increment what our current frame of animation is.
所以我们现在的画面是这一幅 然后0.2秒过去了
So our current frame is this one, and then 0.2 seconds elapses,
就是这一次
it's going to be this one.
然后0.2秒过去了 我们需要循环回到起点
And then 0.2 second elapses, and we need to loop back to the beginning.
所以我们最终会使用模数来解决这个问题
So we'll end up using modulus to take care of that
就像我们在动画课上看到的那样
as we can see in the Animation class.
基本上 这些都在这里完成了
Basically, that's all done here.
因此 如果我们有不止一帧动画 回想一下 它在这里得到了定义
So if we have more than one frame of animation, recall it gets a def here.
所以我们得到帧 我们得到一个间隔 得到一个被初始化为0的计时器
So we get frames, we get an interval, get a timer that's initialized to 0,
然后获得当前帧
and then get a current frame.
我们将当前帧设置为1
We'll say the current frame is 1.
然后 只要我们有不止一帧
And then as long as we have more than one frame,
循环或尝试动画是没有意义的
there's no point in looping over or trying to animate
只有一帧的任何动画
any animation that only has one frame.
当然 我们可以制作只有一帧的动画
And we can, of course, have animations that only have one frame.
闲置只是一帧动画 就像我们在这里看到的
Idle is only one frame of animation, as we saw here.
这只是一帧而已
That's only one frame.
我们不需要做任何逻辑来说 哦
We don't need to do any sort of logic to say, oh,
下一帧是什么 因为只有一帧
what's the next frame, because there's only one frame.
但是如果我们看角色3 我们可以在那里看到两个帧
But if we were to look at character3, we can see two frames there.
然后 这只是一个画面 他无所事事
And then that's just one, frame he's idle.
当我们向左移动时 他也会朝那个方向移动
And when we move left, he moves in that direction.
有没有人记得我们怎么才能找到他--因为很明显
Anybody recall how we can get him-- because obviously,
我们刚刚看到了电子表格
we saw the spreadsheet just a second ago,
而精灵面对的只有一个方向--
and there was only one direction that the sprites were facing--
我们怎么才能让他看起来像那样 即使有
how we can get him to look that way, even though there's
没有精灵让他看起来那样吗？
no sprites for him to look that way?
观众：把它绕着轴翻转
AUDIENCE: Flip it on the axis.
科尔顿·奥格登：翻转它 所以爱
COLTON OGDEN: Flip it, so love.graphics.draw.
回想一下 您可以在任意轴上传递负比例因子
Recall you can pass in a negative scale factor on whatever axis you want,
这将会产生沿着那个轴翻转的结果
and that'll have the result of flipping it along that axis.
这就是我们要做的一切
That's all we're doing.
这是默认的框架 所以我们只是绘制它
So this is the default frame, so we're just drawing it.
然后我们必须保持对他面对的方向的参考
And then we have to keep a reference to whatever direction he's facing.
如果他的方向是正确的 我们将
And if his direction is equal to right, we'll
只需绘制该帧 然后循环处理动画即可
just draw that frame and then loop and process the animation.
如果他面朝左 画它 但也要执行负1变换
If he's facing left, draw it, but also perform a negative 1 transformation
在x轴上
on the x-axis.
就像这样 我们让它奏效了
And just like that, we have that working.
所以我们要做的是--
So all we're doing--
只要有个计时器就行了
just keep a timer.
然后 当计时器超过我们的间隔时 只需增加帧
And then when the timer goes over our interval, just increment the frame.
然后用模数循环到它上面--
And then use modulus to loop back over it--
返回到从1开始
back to starting at 1.
这些都是在这28号线上完成的
And that's all done here on this line 28.
所以你可以再往里面看一点
And so you can look in there a little more
如果你想掌握数学原理
if you want to get a handle on how the math works,
但它只是一个简单的迭代帧集合的序列
but it is just a simple sequence of iterating over a collection of frames
以计时器为基础
based on a timer.
这就产生了这样的效果--就像我之前说过的活页书一样--
And that has the effect-- just like a flip book, as I said earlier--
我们的角色有一个动画和一些生活
of our character having an animation and having some life.
那么 关于这个动画课程是如何运作的 有什么问题吗？
So any questions as to how this animation class works?
观众：渲染是在动画课上吗？
AUDIENCE: The render is in the Animate class?
科尔顿·奥格登：所以不是
COLTON OGDEN: So no.
渲染不在动画类中
The render is not in the animate class.
所以渲染是--
So the render is--
我意识到我在这里没有展示任何真正的Main
I realize I didn't show any actual main here.
我们这里有两个动画 只是一个闲置的动画
We have two animations here, which was just the idle one,
所以我们只传了一帧
so we're just passing in one frame.
我们将它的间隔设为1
We're going to give it an interval of 1.
这并不重要 但为了保持一致性
It's not going to really matter, but just for the sake of consistency,
我们给它一个1的区间--任意的
we're giving it an interval of 1-- arbitrary.
也许我们以后会想要改变他的动画
And maybe we want to change his animation later.
因此 通过在这里设置间隔 我们不会忘记在以后添加一个
So by having an interval here, we won't forget to add one later.
移动的动画--回想一下10和11
Moving animation-- recall 10 and 11.
所以这是在这张纸的最后--
So it's toward the end of the sheet--
两个行走的框架
the two walking frames.
这里的间隔是0.2秒
Interval here is 0.2 seconds.
我们需要一个当前的动画来渲染他
We need a current animation to render him,
然后我们会参考他所看的任何方向
and then we keep a reference to whatever direction he's looking at.
所以如果他向右看 我们就去
So if he's looking to the right, we're going
要在love.graph中引用这一点 请在底部绘制
to reference this in the love.graphics.draw at the bottom.
这就是我们要用来表演精灵翻转的东西
And that's what we're going to use to perform the sprite flipping
沿着x轴
along the x-axis.
保持对这一点的引用
Maintain a reference to that.
然后在这里 我们实际引用动画的部分
And then down here, the part that we actually reference the animation
如果你在看《字符1》 在150号线上
is on line 150 if you're looking at character1.
或者是第二个特征？
Or is it character2?
抱歉 角色3
Sorry, character3.
如果你看的是第三个角色的第150行
If you're looking at line 150 in character3,
我们使用CurrentAnimation：getCurrentFrame()
we're using currentAnimation:getCurrentFrame().
所以这个类实际上只会告诉你动画的当前帧是什么
So the class will actually just tell you whatever the current frame of animation
是因为它保留了对它基于计时器的帧的引用
is, because it keeps a reference to what frame it is based on the timer
以及已经过去了多少
and how much has elapsed.
观众：所以这个班级正在实时生成一个不同的画面
AUDIENCE: So the class is generating a different frame real time
然后把它插在那里
and plugging it in there.
科尔顿·奥格登：是的
COLTON OGDEN: Yeah.
它维护对当前帧的引用
It's maintaining a reference to whatever the current frame is,
它在你给它的时候得到的相框表格里
and it's in the table of frames that it got when you gave it
最上面的定义--
the definition up at the top here--
第51到58行 我们在其中创建两个动画
lines 51 to 58 where we create the two animations.
基本上 它维护对该框架表中哪个索引的引用
Basically, it maintains a reference to which index in this frame table
我们已经到了
we're at.
所以 如果0.2秒过去了 我们从1开始 然后我们转到2
So if 0.2 seconds has elapsed, we start at 1, and then we go to 2.
然后我们将返回到1
And then we'll go back to 1.
所以它基本上只会返回帧和索引
And so it'll just basically return frames, index.
并且帧索引1是10 帧索引2是11
And frames index 1 is 10, frames index 2 is 11.
所以函数是getCurrentFrame
And so the function is getCurrentFrame.
因此Character Quads、CurrentAnimation、GetCurrentFrame
So characterQuads, currentAnimation, getCurrentFrame.
然后在这里 因为我们正在进行原点转换--
And then here, because we're performing an origin transformation--
所以 当你翻转精灵时 这是另一件需要考虑的事情
so that's another thing to consider when you're flipping sprites.
当你翻转一个精灵时 它实际上是顺着它翻转的
When you flip a sprite, it actually flips along
不管它的默认来源是什么
whatever its default origin is.
任何精灵的默认原点都在这里的左上角
And the default origin of any sprite is its top left corner here.
所以如果你沿着x轴翻转某物
So if you flip something along its x-axis,
它会出现在这里 而不是在原地翻转
it'll appear here instead of just flipping in place.
所以实际上你必须将原点设置为其中心
So you actually have to set the origin to its center
当你做任何形式的原地翻转精灵
when you do any sort of in place flipping of a sprite.
因此 当您查看代码时 您会注意到
So you'll notice in the code when you're looking
在这里 我们将字符宽度除以2 再加上字符高度
at it that we have plus CHARACTER_WIDTH divided by 2 and plus CHARACTER_HEIGHT
用这两个除以2
divided by 2 on these two here.
所以我们移动它的绘制位置 然后我们移动它的原点
So we shift where it gets drawn, and then we shift its origin
偏移量在第160行
offsets which are here on line 160.
所以 如果你看love.graph 你会发现
So if you look at love.graphics.draw, you'll
看 它有很多可选参数
see it has a lot of optional arguments.
底部的这两个参数是原点偏移参数
And these two at the bottom are the origin offset arguments.
所以这些只有在以下情况下才真正发挥作用
And so these only really come into play when
你做一些精灵在轴上的翻转
you do some kind of flipping of a sprite on an axis
你想要图形的一致性 而不是让它以这样或那样的方式翻转
and you want graphical consistency not to have it flip one way or the other.
有时这就是你想要的效果 但在这种情况下
Sometimes that's the effect you're looking for, but in this case,
事实并非如此
it's not.
我们希望他呆在原地不动
We want him to literally stay in the exact same place.
因此 要在完全相同的位置翻转一杯雪碧
So to flip a sprite in the exact same place,
您需要将其原点设置在其中心 而不是其左上角
you need a set its origin to its center, not its top left.
这说得通吗？
Does that makes sense?
好的
OK.
还有这里 0是这里的旋转
And also here, 0 is the rotation here.
因此 如果您要添加
So it's sort of required if you're going to add
将这么多参数传递给函数
this many arguments to the function.
但我们正在测试方向是否等于左 我们想要翻到负1
But we're testing if direction is equal to left, we want to flip by negative 1
在x上 否则就给它1
on the x, else just give it 1.
因此 1只是表示默认变换 所以没有翻转
So 1 just means default transformation, so no flipping.
然后我们根本不在y上翻转 所以它永远是1
And then we don't flip on the y at all, so that will always be 1.
简而言之 这就是如何让你的角色动画化 同时
And so that's in a nutshell how you can get your character to animate and also
设置动画时 请保持原地不动
stay in place when you animate it.
那么 有没有关于动画或原点偏移或任何工作原理的问题？
So any questions as to how animations or the origin offsets or any of that work?
好的
OK.
所以我们确实谈到了动画
So we did talk about animations.
我们将讨论的最后一件事是跳跃
The last thing we'll talk about for the character is jumping.
那么 如果你回忆起Flappy Bird 我们怎么才能让我们的角色跳起来呢？
So if you recall from Flappy Bird, how can we get our character to jump?
我们需要些什么呢？
What are some of the pieces we need?
观众：按下键 然后y上升
AUDIENCE: Key press, and then the y goes up.
然后我们必须有重力
And then we have to have gravity.
科尔顿·奥格登：是的
COLTON OGDEN: Yep.
所以按键是我们需要的一件事 所以检查一下空间
So key press is one thing we need, so check for space
将成为默认密钥
is going to be the default key.
Y上升 然后检查重力
y goes up, and then check for gravity.
所以我们不仅需要y 我们还需要
So not only do we need y, but we also need delta y.
我们需要速度 因为重力是速度的变换 而不是
We need velocity, because gravity is a transformation on velocity, not
严阵以待
strictly on position.
所以如果我们回到角色4 这是一种
So if we go back to character4, this is sort
以一种老套的方式来实现重力
of a hackish way of implementing gravity,
因为我们实际上还没有合并瓷砖碰撞
because we haven't actually incorporated tile collisions.
为此 我将推迟大部分实施
And I'll defer most of the implementation for that
至于发行版 我会和你们一起去的
as to the distro, and I'll go over with you guys.
但现在 我们拥有和以前完全一样的东西
But right now, we have the exact same thing we had before,
在那里我们有瓷砖滚动
where we have tile scrolling.
但如果我按空格键 我上去 然后他下来
But if I press space bar, I go up, and then he comes down.
请注意 他也有一个动画
And notice that he has an animation as well.
他有着不同的身材
He has a different frame.
所以如果他在跳跃 他就有一个小小的跳跃框
So if he's jumping, he's got a little jump frame.
这意味着我们现在有三个动画
So that means now we have three animations.
我们有一个闲置的动画 我们有一个移动的动画
We have an idle animation, we have a moving animation,
然后我们有一个跳跃动画
and then we have a jump animation.
所以实际上 我们也有三个州--
So effectively, we have three states as well--
空闲状态、移动状态和跳跃状态
idle state, moving state, and jumping state.
实际上是四个州
Four states, actually.
另外 我注意到这里有一个小错误 如果你还在空中
And also, I noticed a slight bug here where if you're still in the air,
他的框架没有改变
his frame doesn't change.
所以它实际上可能应该停留在那个画面上
So it actually probably should stay to that frame,
即使他站着不动
even if he's standing still.
但我想这没什么大不了的
But I guess it doesn't matter too much.
我们也把它理解为一种特征
We also interpret it as a feature.
但当他在空中飞行时 他有几个状态
But he's got a couple of states when he's in the air.
这里应该有两个州
There should be two states here.
一种是跳跃状态 另一种是下降状态
One is jumping state, and one is falling state.
我们知道为什么两者不同是一件重要的事情吗？
And do we know why the two being different is an important thing?
所以如果我们想一想超级马里奥兄弟
So if we think about Super Mario Bros.
我们思考跳跃和坠落之间的区别
and we think about the differences between jumping and falling,
根据马里奥是否跳跃 有哪些事情会改变
what are some of the things that change based on whether Mario is jumping
或者他是不是在坠落？
or whether he's falling?
我应该说 他与环境的互动有什么不同？
How does he interact differently with the environment, I should say?
所以 如果不熟悉的话 马里奥--当他跳起来的时候 他实际上可以击中盖帽
So if unfamiliar, Mario-- when he jumps, he can actually hit blocks.
因此 如果他在一个街区下面 他击中了一个街区
So if he's below a block and he hits a block that
它有某种行为 它会触发那个区块中的任何东西
has some sort of behavior in it, it will trigger whatever is in that block,
不管它是一枚硬币 还是要毁掉这个街区
whether it's a coin or whether it's to destroy the block.
如果他倒下了 回想一下如果他像野猪一样落在敌人身上
And if he's falling, recall if he lands on top of an enemy like a goomba,
他会消灭敌人
he'll destroy the enemy.
因此 我们需要区分这两种状态
And so we need to distinguish between these two states.
因为当他跳的时候 他不能--
Because when he's jumping, he's not able to--
当他真的飞起来的时候 他不能攻击敌人
when he's actually going up, he can't attack the enemy.
同样 当他倒下时 他不能摧毁街区
And likewise, when he's falling down, he can't destroy the block.
所以即使他在空中跳跃
So even though he's jumping up in the air
重力正在应用一种变换
and the gravity is applying a transformation
这一切看起来都像是一个州 实际上有两个重要的变化
and it all looks like one state, there's actually two important changes
在他所在的州都是相关的
in his state that are relevant.
这是我们需要注意的事情
And that's something that we'll need to pay attention to,
而且它在发行版中
and it's in the distro.
他有跌倒状态和跳跃状态
He has a falling state and a jumping state.
即使它们共享相同的动画
Even though they share the same animation,
他们有不同的行为
they have different behavior.
因此 让我们继续查看这里的Character 4发行版
So let's go ahead and look at the character4 distro here.
所以我在这里做的是 我为这个角色添加了一个增量y
So what I've done here is I've added a delta y for the character.
所以就像在Flappy Bird中我们按空格键一样
So just like in Flappy Bird when we press space
我们的增量y上升到负50--
and we made our delta y go up to negative 50--
所以立刻涨到了相当高的水平 因为
so instantly shot up pretty high, because that was getting
适用于每一帧
applied every frame.
这里也是一样
Same thing here.
一旦我们按下空格键 我们将把增量y改为负50
Once we press space, we're going to change delta y to negative 50
如果我们往下走到这里
if we go down to right here.
因此 如果键等于空格 我将它放在love.keyPressed函数中
So if the key is equal to space, I have it in the love.keyPressed function.
因为我们是在Main.Lua中做这一切 只是为了说明
Since we're doing all this in main.lua just for illustration,
事情有点简单
things are a little simple.
如果密钥等于空间并且他的增量y是
If key is equal to space and his delta y is
等于0 如果我们不这样做会发生什么
equal to 0, what would happen if we didn't
检查增量y是否等于0？
check to see if delta y was equal to 0?
观众：我们在空中双人跳跃
AUDIENCE: We double jump in the air.
科尔顿·奥格登：是的
COLTON OGDEN: Yep.
我们将能够无限跳跃 所以我们必须对此进行检查
We'd be able to jump infinitely, so we have to do a check for that.
我们把他的速度调到了跳跃速度
We set his dy to JUMP_VELOCITY.
JUMP_SPECTURE是第29行上的一个常量 它是负200
JUMP_VELOCITY is a constant up top on line 29, which is negative 200.
重力等于7
And then gravity is equal to 7.
所以我们要做的就是把它设置为负200--他的增量y--
And so what we do is we set it to negative 200-- his delta y--
只要他一跳起来
as soon as he jumps.
然后更新中的每一帧 我们基本上
And then every frame down in update, we basically
通过重力增加他的增量y
increment his delta y by gravity.
然后我们把他的y增加 乘以
And then we increment his y by delta y times delta time.
所以它的效果就是当他在空中时
And so it'll have the effect of when he's in the air
他的速度是负的 实际上
and he's got a negative velocity, it'll actually
开始变得越来越积极 直到它变得积极
start becoming positive and positive until it is positive,
然后他倒在地上
and then he falls back to the ground.
然后是我之前提到的黑客攻击--
And then the hack that I was referring to earlier--
因为我们还没有在这个例子中实现碰撞检测--
since we don't have collision detection implemented in this example yet--
我们只是想看看他有没有
is we're just basically checking to see whether he has
低于我们设定的地图底线
gone below what we set the map's floor.
如果他有 那么首先把他的位置设定在那块瓷砖的上方
And if he has, then set his position, first of all, to be above that tile
这里是133线
here on line 133.
然后将他的增量y设为0
And then set his delta y equal to 0.
这将允许我们再次进入太空
And that will allow us then to hit space again,
因为他的增量y等于0
because his delta y will be equal to 0.
观众：所以我没有在上面看到[INAUDIBLE]
AUDIENCE: So I didn't see [INAUDIBLE] on it.
那么 看起来总是有重力存在
Looks like there's always gravity, then.
科尔顿·奥格登：总会有重力 某种东西
COLTON OGDEN: There is always gravity, something
我在演讲前不久意识到
I realized shortly before lecture.
但我认为 你真正需要做的就是 如果角色死了--
But all you would really have to do is, I think, if character dy--
嗯
Yeah.
您可以很容易地将其提取出来--只需围绕它添加一条if语句
You could easily take that out of there-- just an if statement around it.
观众：这只是浪费资源 对吗？
AUDIENCE: It's just a waste of resources, right?
科尔顿·奥格登：是的
COLTON OGDEN: It is.
我是说 这并不贵 因为你所做的
I mean, it's not expensive, because all you're doing
是将变量递增一定的量
is incrementing a variable by a certain amount.
如果说有什么不同的话 那就是如果你每一帧都要引入一个IF条件
If anything, if you're introducing an if condition every frame,
即使不是更多 也可能是相同的
which is probably the same if not actually more.
我认为分支更像是CPU 而不仅仅是一个赋值
I think a branch is more CPU than just an assignment.
对于这一点 我不是完全确定
I'm not entirely sure about that.
观众：很有趣
AUDIENCE: Interesting.
科尔顿·奥格登：是的
COLTON OGDEN: Yeah.
在这种情况下 它实际上没有任何副作用
In this case, it doesn't really have any side effects.
但值得注意的是 这是一件好事
But it's a good thing to notice.
但现在请注意 我们可以沿着这里的地板走
But now notice that we can just sort of walk along the floor here,
因为没有碰撞检测
because there's no collision detection.
我们将很快讨论如何实现冲突检测
We'll talk about how we implement a collision detection soon.
所以我们要开始讨论的一件事--我们会好好休息一下
So one thing that we'll start talking on-- and we'll take a break fairly
很快--
soon--
是程序级生成
is procedural level generation.
所以我是程序级生成的铁杆粉丝
So I am a big fan of procedural level generation,
而平台级别实际上相当容易--
and platformer levels are actually fairly easy--
至少在简单的意义上--
at least in a simple sense--
在程序上产生
to procedurally generate.
所以就像第三场比赛一样 我们基本上
And so like with match three, all we basically
只是在我们的网格中循环 然后
did was just loop through our grid and just
比方说 哦 得到一个随机的颜色和一个随机的变化
say, oh, get a random color and a random variety.
然后在任务中 事情变得有点复杂
And then with the assignment, it was a little bit more complicated,
在那里 你必须检查你是否处于第一级
where you actually had to check to see whether you were on level one.
如果你不是 那么你的品种
And then if you weren't, then your variety
应该是一定的数量 这取决于你已经走了多远
should be maybe a certain amount depending on how far along you've
在比赛中取得了进步
progressed in the game.
有了平台级别 我们必须考虑
With a platformer level, we have to think
关于我们如何利用磁贴ID的网格 并从数学上考虑它
about how we can take that grid of tile IDs and think about it mathematically.
我们如何才能得到一个级别的结果 但每次都让它不同--
How can we get the results of a level, but make it different every time--
引入一些变种 对吗？
introduce some variation, right?
所以我找到的解决方案是最有意义的
And so the solution that I found that makes the most sense
是一列接一列地进行
is going column by column.
所以在这里 我们只有一堆--这只是
So here, we just have a bunch of-- this is just
一个非常简单的完美屏幕截图来说明一个非常简单的方式
a very simple perfect screenshot to illustrate a very simple way
生成标高的能力
of generating the level.
但请记住 如果我们只考虑这些瓷砖--这些空白空间--
But recall, if we just think about these tiles here-- these empty spaces--
作为0 而这些是1 在这种情况下 它几乎是二进制的
being a 0 and these being a 1, it's sort of almost like binary in this case.
我们可以先用0填充整个空间 只需假定为空
We could just fill the entire thing with 0 first, just assume empty space.
然后我们可以一列一列地往下走 只有一个机会
And then we could just column by column go down and just have a chance
每一列
every column.
好的 我要在这里建一个地面吗？
OK, do I want to generate a ground here?
如果我这样做了 从底层开始 然后
If I do, start at the ground level and then just
一直向下生成土砖
generate earth tiles all the way down.
然后转到下一个x位置 做同样的事情 做同样的事情
And then go to the next x position, do the same thing, do the same thing.
然后 也许你产生的世界上的每一列
And then maybe every column of the world that you're generating,
你也有机会产生这样的支柱
you also have a chance to generate a pillar like this.
因此 如果生成支柱是真的 那么我想要产生--
So if generate pillar is true, then I want to spawn--
我想从这里开始 而不是从这里开始
instead of starting the ground here, I want to start it here.
然后你可能会有一面旗子上写着
And then maybe you have a flag that says,
好的 我不仅想要产生柱子
OK, not only do I want to generate pillars,
我还想生成裂缝--
I also want to generate chasms--
只有空旷的空间 对球员来说是障碍
just empty space, obstacles for the player.
因为如果他掉下来--掉到世界空间之下--
Because if he falls down-- it goes below the world space--
游戏就该结束了
it should be game over.
那么这样的话 你就说如果产生鸿沟--
So in that case, you just say if generate chasm--
做数学 随机10或其他什么--
make math.random 10 or whatever it is--
那就去下一个x
then just go to the next x.
什么都别做
Don't even do anything.
这将产生一个鸿沟的结果
And that will have the result of generating a chasm.
一点点地
And so little piece by piece--
做这样的小事
doing small things like that has the net effect
产生了很多视觉上有趣的 动态的
of generating a lot of visually interesting, dynamic,
和随机水平
and random levels.
你永远不知道会发生什么
You never know what to expect.
这是一个非常基本的例子
And this is a very basic example.
你可以用它无限远
You could go infinitely far with it.
不管你有多少关于如何
However many ideas you have in terms of how
为玩家创造障碍、有趣的关卡和风景--
to create obstacles and interesting levels and scenery for the player--
你完全可以实现它
you could absolutely implement that.
观众：如果有一个平台可以跳上去 你怎么处理？
AUDIENCE: How do you handle if there's a platform to jump on?
你必须有这种一致性
You have to have that consistency.
是的
COLTON OGDEN: Yeah.
所以如果它是一个平台 这取决于你想如何实现平台
So if it's a platform, it depends on how you want to implement platforms.
实际上 我参加了一个关于超级马里奥兄弟的研讨会
And actually, I did a seminar on Super Mario Bros.,
我们把平台做成瓷砖
and we did platforms as tiles.
在这种情况下 我们将有块 实际上是
In this case, we'll have blocks that are actually
我们称之为游戏对象--
what we've denoted as game objects-- which
和瓷砖有点不同
are a little bit different than tiles.
因为它们可以有任意的大小 而且它们不一定
Because they can have arbitrary sizes, and they don't necessarily
都必须连接到世界电网上
have to be affixed to the world grid.
但是如果你要把一个平台 比如说
But if you were to treat a platform that was, let's say,
两块瓷砖那么宽 你要做的就是
two tiles wide as tiles, all you would do
基本上就是在这里有一个标志 就像 生成平台
is just basically have a flag up here that's like, generate platform
等于真或者别的什么
equals true or whatever--
观众：然后关掉它
AUDIENCE: And then turn it off after--
科尔顿·奥格登：不管迭代多少次 都要把它关掉
COLTON OGDEN: Turn it off after however many iterations.
你也需要它的大小
You also need the size of it.
你需要一面旗子 就像平台宽度等于多少
You'll need a flag that's like platform width equals however many,
所以你只需要保留一个计数器
and so you'll just keep a counter.
就像当前平台瓦片等于1 2 3
It's like current platform tile equals 1, 2, 3.
如果它等于width 那么你就不会再生成它了
And if it's equal to width, then you don't generate it any more.
这就有可能与柱子相撞
And that has the effect of potentially colliding with pillars
如果你不考虑这个的话
if you don't account for that.
所以你也可以在你的逻辑中说 如果我现在正在生成一个平台
So you can also in your logic say, if I'm generating a platform right now,
不要产生柱子
don't generate a pillar.
但你可能会产生一个裂缝 因为这个裂缝
But you could generate a chasm, because the chasm
不会干扰您的平台
doesn't interfere with your platform.
如果你没有平台作为瓷砖--如果它们是不同的物体--
If you don't have platforms as tiles-- if they're different objects--
那么 您就不必在实际的世界生成阶段这样做了
then you don't have to do it during the actual world generation phase.
你可以直接测试一下
You can just test.
你可以只创建一个游戏对象 这是一个平台
You can just create a game object that's a platform.
取决于你的算法有多复杂
Depending on how complicated your algorithm is,
也许当你生成它的时候 要确保它不在柱子旁边
maybe make sure that it's not next to a pillar when you generate it.
你可以把瓷砖放在这里 然后看一看
And you could just do that by getting the tile here and then looking
在接下来的四块瓷砖上--
at the next four tiles--
差不多就是这样
something like that.
在本例中 我们不使用平台 但它是
We don't do platforms in this example, but it's something
你可以很容易地用瓷砖做到这一点
that you could pretty easily do with tiles.
虽然难度稍大 但仍相当容易
And slightly more difficult but also still fairly easy to
处理游戏对象 它包含在发行版中
do with game objects, which is included in the distro
我们稍后会谈到这一点
and which we'll touch on in a little bit.
让我们看看 我们在一个水平上--
Let's see, we're at level--
哦 在我们开始之前我还有几件事想展示
oh, another couple of things that I wanted to show before we
实际上 开始学习如何生成关卡的代码
actually start getting into the code for how to generate levels.
这是整个项目的精灵工作表 这是一个非常酷的精灵
This is the sprite sheet for this whole project, which is a really cool sprite
我在网上找到的一张纸
sheet that I found online.
这是在马里奥这样的平台上的精神
It's in the spirit of platformers like Mario,
它的右边有一个很好的小模型
and it's got a nice little mockup here on the right.
所以我鼓励你们看看这一点
So I encourage you to take a look at that
也许会得到一些灵感 看看所有不同的酷东西
and just maybe get some inspiration and see all the different cool stuff.
如果你想的话 可以随便修修补补
Tinker around with it if you want to.
但正如你在这里看到的 有几个非常突出的事情
But as you can see here, there's a couple of pretty prominent things.
我们有一吨的瓷砖
We have a ton of tiles.
这些都是瓷砖--
These are all tiles here--
不同的瓷砖和变体
different tiles and variations.
然后我们这里有一大堆这样的浇头
And then we have a ton of these toppers here.
所以真正帮助整个演示的是
And so what really helps this whole demonstration
产生这些能级的一个事实是 我们有
of generating these levels is the fact that we have
要处理的视觉内容太多了
so much visual content to work with.
这里 再一次 是瓷砖
And so here, again, are the tiles.
这是上等菜
Here are the toppers.
然后当你把这两者放在一起 然后你也
And then when you take the two together and then you also
有这些随机的背景--
have these random backgrounds--
这些是顶层 这里是瓷砖的顶层
these are toppers here, the top of the tiles here.
仅仅拥有丰富的视觉多样性是令人难以置信的容易
It's incredibly easy to just have a sheer abundance of visual variety
和有趣的东西 在你的游戏水平 甚至没有--
and interesting things in your game levels without even--
这里的算法非常简单
and the algorithms here are very simple.
我们所做的只是检查以生成柱子和柱子
All we're doing is just checking to generate pillars and columns.
我知道呀
I know.
我认为这真的很酷 有助于说明
I thought it was really cool and helps illustrate the importance and power
整个程序性的方法来为这个创造层次
of this whole procedural approach to creating the levels for this.
我认为 实际上并没有那么多的游戏可以利用这一点
And there's actually not that many games that take advantage, I think,
在平台类型中的程序级生成
of procedural level generation in the platformer genre.
很多游戏 比如《我的世界》和《Terraria》--
Plenty of games like Minecraft and Terraria--
Terraria就是一个很好的平台 这就是一个例子
Terraria is a great platformer that is an example of that.
但我不认为我见过真正好的超级马里奥兄弟
But I don't think I've seen a really good Super Mario Bros.
这样做的游戏
game that does something like that.
让我们看看
Let's see.
现在几点？
What time is it?
6：23
6:23.
让我们休息五分钟
Let's take a five minute.
然后我们一从那里回来
And then as soon as we get back from that,
我们将开始研究如何真正实现程序级
we'll start going into how we actually can implement the procedural level
更详细的生成
generation in more detail.
好了 欢迎回来
All right, welcome back.
这是第四课
This is lecture four.
在我们休息之前 我们聊了聊
And before we took a break, we were talking
关于平台级别上下文中的程序级别生成
about procedural level generation in the context of platformer levels.
回想一下 这里只有几个例子 我很快就用了我的代码
So recall, here are just a few examples that I took pretty quickly of my code.
你可以看到它们有不同的背景 不同的瓷砖
And you can see they have different backgrounds, different tiles.
有时我们有裂缝 有时我们有支柱
Sometimes we have chasms, sometimes we have pillars.
我们将讨论几种方法来实现这一点
We'll be talking about a few ways to do the tile version of that,
因为这里有两个层次
because there's two levels here.
例如 在发行版中 我们会看到也有灌木丛之类的东西
In the distro, we'll see there are also things like bushes, for example.
我们可以在中间上方看到紫色的--
We can see in the top middle there the purple--
我猜那些紫色的小仙人掌
well, I guess those little purple cacti.
而在它的正下方 有一根柱子 上面有一根黄色的蕨类植物
And the one right below that, there is a pillar with a yellow fern on it.
这些是与瓷砖分开的物体--
Those are separate objects from the tiles--
游戏对象
game objects.
但实际的瓷砖本身 我们将在这里稍微挖掘一下如何
But the actual tiles themselves we'll dig in here a little bit as to how
才能让它们产生
to get those generated.
所以我们首先要看的是水平0 只是一些平坦的水平--所以
So the first thing we want to look at, level0, is just some flat levels-- so
基本上就是我们已经做过的
just basically what we've already done.
所以我要继续 进入0级
So I'm going to go ahead and go into level0.
然后如果我们看到这里 我们有一个简单的平坦的水平
And then if we see here, we have a simple flat level,
就像我们以前做的那样
just like we did before.
现在瓷砖不同了
Now the tiles are different.
如果我按R键 它们每次都会随机生成
And if I press R, they're randomly generating every time.
所以你可以感受到这一代人在视觉上看起来有多多样化
So you can get a sense of just how visually diverse this generation looks.
哦 我想这可能是之前的一个漏洞
Oh, I think that might have been a bug earlier.
我没有把握
I'm not sure.
我还没看过呢
Haven't seen that yet.
但我们可以在这里看到 我在按R键
But we can see here, I'm pressing R.
我要做的就是把我们拥有的瓷砖阵列
All I'm doing is taking the array of tiles that we have,
我给它分配了一套瓷砖和一套顶层
and I'm assigning it a tile set and a topper set
在这一代的范围的情况下
in the case of the scope of this generation.
回想一下 顶层只是顶层的精灵
So recall that the topper is just the top layer sprite,
瓷砖就是下面的瓷砖
and the tile set is the tiles underneath.
有没有人想建议我是如何渲染顶层和瓷砖的
Anybody want to just suggest how I'm rendering the topper versus the tiles
那里发生了什么事？
and what's going on there?
观众：你只是把它从床单的一部分拉出来 对吗？
AUDIENCE: You're just pulling it from part of the sheet, right?
科尔顿·奥格登：是的
COLTON OGDEN: Yes.
是的 简而言之 我只是在拉开盖子
Yeah, in a nutshell, I'm just pulling the toppers
从床单的不同部分
from a different part of the sheet.
你知道我是如何存储信息的吗--这里存储了什么
Any idea how I'm storing information-- what's being stored here
才能让它像这样渲染？
to get it to render like this?
观众：也许你只需要把陀螺的位置储存起来
AUDIENCE: Maybe you just need to store the position of the topper
并知道其他一切都低于这一点
and know that everything else is below that.
科尔顿·奥格登：是的
COLTON OGDEN: Yes.
这样你就可以存储顶部的位置
So you could store the position of the topper
并知道其他一切都低于这一点
and know that everything else is below that.
这将适用于平坦的水平
That would work for a flat level.
我认为对于有柱子的楼层来说 这是不可靠的
I don't think that would be reliable for a level that has pillars on it,
因为柱子的高度比地面高
because the pillars are a higher elevation than the ground.
然后还有裂缝之类的东西
And then there's also chasms and stuff like that.
所以实际上这里发生的事情是我们
So what's going on here actually is we're
在瓷砖上存储一面旗帜 说明上面是否有顶层
storing a flag in the tile that says whether or not it has a topper on it.
如果它有顶部 那么我们不仅渲染瓷砖
And if it has a topper, then we render not only the tile,
但一旦我们渲染了瓷砖 我们也渲染了顶部
but as soon as we render the tile, we also render the topper.
在这里 我不会深入到代码中
And I won't go too deep into the code here.
但我们正在做的是让所有这些不同的瓷砖集和顶层集
But what we're doing to get all these different tile sets and topper sets
还有就是我们必须把所有这些瓷砖--这些瓷砖的集合--
too is we have to take all of these tile sets-- these collections of tiles--
然后把它们分了 对吗？
and divide them up, right?
我们必须知道 如果我们想要以瓷砖呈现整个关卡
We have to know that if we want to render the entire level in tile
设置一个 那么我们基本上应该把这个放到它自己的工作表上--
set one, then we should basically take this into its own sheet--
它自己的表--这个放到自己的表里 这个放到自己的表里
its own table-- this into its own table, this into its own table, going
实际上是从左到右
left to right actually.
我们基本上有四路嵌套循环
And we have basically four way nested loop.
所以我们用x上的每一组来计算y上的每一组
So we go every set on the x by every set on the y.
然后在其中的每一个中 我们要查找沿x的每一块瓷砖
And then within each of those, we want to look for every tile along the x
和沿y方向的每一块瓷砖 并分开
and every tile along the y therein and split up
瓷砖设置 这样我们就可以索引到单独的四边形
the tile sets so that we can index into the individual quads.
所以在实际的代码中 我不会在这里深入研究它
So in the actual code, I won't go too deeply into it here.
但如果你对我们是如何做到这一点感兴趣的 我可以带你去看看
But I'll show you where it is if you're curious to look into how we do that.
它在源代码中的马里奥 util.lua 这是我们以前回忆起的地方
It's in Mario in Source, util.lua, which is recall where we before
存储了我们的GenerateQuads函数 该函数对切片执行简单的拆分
stored our generateQuads function, which does a simple split on a tile
根据传入的宽度和高度沿其x和y方向放置工作表
sheet along its x and y based on whatever width and height you pass in.
这里还有一个GenerateTileSets函数 它接受四元组
We have in here also a generateTileSets function, which takes in the quads
来自GenerateQuads表的
from a generateQuads table.
因此 我们首先在所有这些或所有这些上生成四元组
So we first generate quads on all of this or all of this.
所以我们把每一帧都除以16 这就是--
So we have every single frame of this divided by 16, which is--
我不知道那有多少
I don't know how many that is.
6乘5乘10乘5 10乘4--
6 by 5 times 10 by 5, 10 by 4--
那么多四元 所以成千上万的四元 我想 如果不是几百的话
that many quads, so thousands of quads, I think, if not hundreds.
我敢肯定这是几千个四元房
This I'm pretty sure is thousands of quads.
然后我们把它取出来 然后用
And then we take that and then divide it using
沿x轴的集合的数目 y轴上的集合的数目
the number of sets along the x-axis, sets on the y-axis,
然后每个瓷砖的大小沿x设置 沿y设置大小
and then the size of each tile set along the x and size along the y.
在这里 我们基本上使用一个四向嵌套循环来划分它
We basically divide it using a four way nested loop here.
我们基本上只是把它分了
We basically just divide it up.
然后 不是做GenerateQuad
And then instead of doing a generateQuads
在整个画面中 我们只是
along the entirety of the picture, we just
基本上对我们得到的四元桌做一个2D切片
basically do a 2D slice of that quad table we get back
从第一个genateQuad调用开始
from the first generateQuads call.
所以我鼓励你们看看这里 并尝试一下
So I encourage you to look in here and experiment with that.
你不一定需要知道它在任务中是如何工作的
You don't need to necessarily know how it works for the assignment.
但这就是我们基本上可以拿到像这样的巨型床单的方式
But that's how we can basically take a giant sheet like this
并轻松地将其集成到我们的代码中
and easily integrate it into our code.
我们只需换入和换出任何活动磁贴
We can just swap in and out whatever active tile
我们想要处理的工作表 假设一切
sheet we want to work with, assuming that everything
像这样干净地布局 这是你或你的艺术家的一部分
is cleanly laid out like this, which is on the part of you or your artist.
你要确保一切都有利于程序化的组织
You want to make sure that everything is conducive to programmatic organization.
如果东西以一种非常尴尬的方式散布--
Had things been scattered around in a very awkward way--
也许东西是之字形的 或者有奇怪的空间或类似的东西
maybe things were zig zagged or there were weird spaces or something like
那个--
that--
我们不能做像我们在这里做的那样干净的事情
we wouldn't be able to do something as clean as what we did here
Util.lua中只有63减去20行代码
in util.lua with just 63 minus 20 lines of code
通过获取每个单独的瓷砖集
by getting each individual tile set.
所以这是一个重要的考虑因素
So that's an important consideration if you're
考虑为您的项目创建资产
looking at creating assets for your project
并且您想要对您的磁贴集进行一些程序化的热交换
and you want to do some programmatic hot swapping of your tile sets.
让我们确保我们是对的--
Let's make sure we're in the right--
我们在这里不是正确的例子 所以我们
we're not in the right example here, so we're
进入0层进入主干道
going to go into level0 into main.
现在我们有了所有瓷砖的常量 高度是多少
And we have constants now for all of our tile sets and what the height is
以及它们有多少是宽到高的
and how many they are wide by tall.
我们在这里做
We do it here.
我们从我们的瓷砖和鞋面上拿到我们的普通四元房
We get our regular quads from our tiles and toppers,
所以这些就是那块大瓷砖里的每一块瓷砖
so these are just literally every single tile within that big tile
把床单放在一张桌子上
sheet put in one table.
然后我们就分成了几组瓷砖
And then we just divided up into tile sets
和topper集 在这里使用GenerateTileSets函数
and topper sets here with generateTileSets function.
然后我们得到一个随机的瓦片集和一个随机的顶层集--
And then we get a random tile set and a random topper set here--
随机数、瓦片集的数目、顶层集的数目
math.random, number of tile sets, number of topper sets.
在最下面 我们有一个GenerateLevel函数--
And then at the very bottom also, we have a generateLevel function--
223--它将在接下来的两个示例中构建
223-- which is going to be built upon in the next two examples.
0级只是一个平坦的级别 所以实际上
Level0 is just a flat level, so it's actually
这就是我们之前看到的 如果y小于7
exactly what we saw before, which was just if y is less than 7,
ID应等于天空或地面
ID should be equal to sky or ground.
然后这一部分实际上就是我
And then this part is actually what I was
用最上面的词暗指之前 因为回忆起
alluding to before with the topper, because recall
我们需要在瓷砖中存储一面旗帜来渲染或不渲染顶部
we need to store a flag in a tile to render a topper or not.
它应该是地面上最上面的瓷砖是什么
And it should be whatever the top tile is in the level on the ground.
在这个非常简单的扁平物体中 我们总是可以
In this very simple flat thing, we can always
假设它将是相同的y能级
assume it'll be the same y level.
在本例中 如果它等于7 则topper
In this case, if it's equal to 7, then topper
应为真 否则为假
should be true, otherwise, false.
所以沿y7的每一块瓷砖的topper都等于真
So every tile along y 7 is going to have topper equals true.
这一点在这里发挥了作用
And this comes into play up here.
如果我们真的爱 我们就不仅仅像以前那样拥有了.ID
If we do love.graphics.draw(tilesheet), we have not only just tile.ID as we did
以前 但我们现在有瓷砖集索引到瓷砖集
before, but we have tile sets indexed into tileset now.
请记住 tieset获得的随机值介于1
So remember, tileset got a random value between 1
不管我们从巨大的瓷砖上拼接出多少瓷砖
and however many tile sets we had that we spliced out of our massive tile
床单
sheet.
现在 我们只需对其进行索引 然后再对tile.id进行索引
Now, we just index into that, and then we index into tile.ID.
而tile.ID将是我们的ID 但相对于该工作表 而不是
And tile.ID will then be whatever our ID is but relative to that sheet, not
一下子把整个精灵都干掉了
the whole entire sprite at once.
托珀也是如此
And the same thing for topper.
我们有一个TOPER集合 我们索引到TOPER
We have a topper set, we index into topper
在我们得到的最上面的一组 然后就是
sets here at the topper set that we got, and then that's
在那里我们将拥有组成特定集合的瓷砖集合
where we'll have the collection of tiles that form that particular set.
因此 这两者是完全分开的
And so the two are completely separate.
它们可以是一个随机颜色的瓷砖和一个随机的顶层 但它是一致的
They can be one random color tile with one random topper, but it's consistent.
这是全球性的
It's global.
我们有一套顶层和一套瓷砖 它们在任何时候都是活动的
We have one topper set and one tile set that are active at any one time.
如果我们按R键 就像我在上面做的那样 那么我们
And if we press R, which I did up here, then we
只需在139和140行将它们重置为随机
just reset them to random on line 139 and 140.
瓦集得到一个新的随机数 TOPER集得到一个新的随机数
Tile set gets a new random number, topper set gets a new random number.
它的效果是--
It has the effect of--
我们可以四处走动 然后生成随机集
we can just walk around and then generate random sets.
太简单了
So pretty simple.
再回想一下 托珀是--
And recall again, topper is--
因为我们脚下的瓷砖是y 7 topper等于true
because the tile that we're standing on is y seven, topper equals true.
所以在这种情况下 特定的顶层总是会有一个顶层
So in that case, that particular top layer is always going to have a topper.
它给了我们一个很好的视觉变化
And it gives us a nice little bit of visual variety,
因为它实际上会产生很大的不同
because it actually makes quite a bit of a difference having
一个加顶的和一个不加顶的
a topper versus no topper.
你也可以不戴帽子
And you can also just not have a topper and consider
这是一个排列的toppers倍瓷砖 像程序算法
that a permutation of the toppers times tiles, like procedural algorithm.
这是平坦的水平
That's flat levels.
有谁对这是怎么运作的有任何疑问吗
Does anybody have any questions as to how this works
或者我们在这里做的任何事
or anything that we're doing here?
好的.
OK.
所以事情有点平淡 有点无聊
So things are a little flat, a little boring.
下一步我们要介绍的是
The next step will be actually introducing one of the things
我们可以在这里看到我们的样本水平的小集合
that we can see here in our little collection of sample levels,
就像中间的这根柱子
like this pillar right here in the very middle.
有谁记得我们是怎么产生一个柱子的
Does anybody recall how we go about spawning a pillar as opposed
变成平地
to just flat land?
观众：对于那一栏 只是把一些更多的污垢或更多的瓷砖下来
AUDIENCE: For that column, just put some more dirt down or more tiles down.
是的
COLTON OGDEN: Yep.
因此 对于这一列 只是把更多的瓷砖下来 而不仅仅是地面水平
So for that column, just put more tiles down instead of just the ground level.
这正是我们要做的
That's exactly what we're going to do.
所以我要打开一楼和主干道
So I'm going to go ahead and open up level1 and main,
我也会运行这个例子 这样你们就能看到它是什么样子的
and I'll run the example here as well just so you can see it looks like.
这里我们有不少
So here we have quite a few.
注意我们还没有实现碰撞
And notice we haven't implement collision,
所以我们还在查
so we're still walking through them.
但他们只是随机的
But they're just random.
它们的随机数量取决于口味 真的
Their random amount is up to taste, really.
在这里很常见 所以可能值得
Right here it's pretty common, so it might be worth
把数量降低一点
lowering the amount a little bit.
如果你想的话 你也可以有一面旗帜 上面写着 产卵之柱
If you wanted to, you could also maybe have a flag that says, spawn pillar,
也许你想要一个支柱宽度
and maybe you want a pillar width.
你可以有一个到三个瓷砖之间的任何地方
You could have anywhere between one and three tiles.
如果它的宽度大于1 那么只需循环几次
And if its width is greater than 1, then just loop over a few times
把同一高度画几次而不是一次
and just draw that same height a few times as opposed to just one time,
然后将标志设回false
and then set the flag back to false.
你可以用它做很多事情
A lot of things you can do with it.
而且这里有点高
And also, they're a little tall here.
对于主要发行版 我最终使它们变短了一点
For the main distro, I ended up making them a little shorter.
但我们将在代码中看到如何做到这一点
But we'll see how we do this in the code here.
它主要在我们的generateLevel函数中
It's going to mostly be down in our generateLevel function.
所以我们在这里做的--继续隐藏--
So what we're doing here-- go ahead and hide that--
我们有一个基本的代码--
is we have basically this code here--
第227至236行
line 227 to 236.
所以我们要做的就是用天空填满整个空间
So all we're doing here is just filling our entire thing with just sky.
我们只是把它设为空
We're just setting the entire thing to empty.
现在我们有一个完全填充的2D数组
And now we have a fully populated 2D array.
我们要做的就是改变瓷砖--我们
All we need to do in order to change a tile-- we
不必担心插入或添加太多的瓷砖到我们的数组
don't have to worry about insertions or adding too many tiles to our array.
我们现在所能做的就是直接改变那里存在的任何瓷砖
All we can do now is just directly change whatever tile exists there.
所以我们要做的就是从239行开始
So all we need to do is starting on line 239,
我们将开始在整个级别上逐列迭代
we're going to start doing the column by column iteration over our entire level
并决定我们是否应该建立支柱
and deciding whether we should generate pillars or not.
我们总是会产生地面
And we're always going to generate ground.
这是旗帜衍生柱
So here's the flag spawnPillar.
如果它等于1 这基本上会被分配给spawnPillar
And if it's equal to 1, this is going to basically be assigned to spawnPillar.
所以math.random（5）==1.
So math.random(5)==1.
我们有五分之一的机会产生一个柱子
We have a 1 in 5 chance of spawning a pillar.
如果我们只需要一个柱子 那么柱子从4到6等于4--
If we just want a pillar, then pillar gets equal to 4 from 4 to 6--
所以y等于4到6
so y gets 4 to 6 effectively--
x柱上的瓷砖 ID地面
tiles at pillar x, ID ground.
然后在这里我们设置顶部 回忆一下
And then here's where we set the topper, recall,
因为现在柱子可以是表面上最上面的瓦片
because now pillars can be the top most tile on the surface.
但它们在地面以上
But they're above the ground level.
所以我们基本上就是说 当我们生成一个柱子时
So we just basically say, when we're generating a pillar,
如果pillar等于4--也就是我们开始的第一个瓦片--
if pillar is equal to 4-- which is the very first tile that we start at--
然后在这里设置topper等于true
then set topper equal to true here.
否则 将其设置为false
Otherwise, set it to false.
所以这就是我们如何让柱子也有顶部 然后在这种情况下
So that's how we can get pillars to also have toppers and then in this case,
我们还没有产生任何裂缝
we're not generating any chasms yet.
所以我们要做的就是
So all we're going to do--
一旦我们在那个特定的柱子上生成了一个柱子
once we've generated a pillar on that particular column,
我们就说地是7直到地图的高度
we'll just say ground gets 7 until the map height--
因此 在屏幕的最底部
so towards the very bottom of the screen.
然后我们就把它放在地面上
And then we'll just set it to ground.
在这种情况下 我们要确保
And then topper-- in this case, we're going to make sure
我们不是在生一根柱子
that we're not spawning a pillar.
因为如果我们不检查这个 它就会
Because if we don't check this, then it'll
在柱子与地面相接的地方也会产生一个顶端
also spawn a topper where the pillar meets the ground,
这看起来会有点傻
and it'll look a little bit silly.
然后我们还想检查地面是否等于7
And then we also want to check that ground is equal to 7.
所以加在一起 这就产生了这种行为的影响
And so all together, that has the effect of this behavior.
因此 如果我们不检查那个产卵支柱
And so if we didn't check for that spawnPillar,
我们的脚下也会有一个鞋帽
we'd have a topper right below our feet here too,
这看起来很奇怪
which looks graphically strange.
而且 你也可以看到--
And also, you can see--
紧急情况下 我们得到了两倍宽的柱子
emergently, we're getting double width pillars.
这只是一种天然的副产品
And that's just kind of a natural byproduct
很多这样的随机化
of a lot of these randomizations.
很多这样的程序性算法--
A lot of these procedural algorithms--
他们会产生你可能不一定会产生的结果
they'll generate outcomes that you might not necessarily
这是一件很酷的事情
have anticipated, which is kind of a cool thing.
你不必给它编程 让它有两块瓷砖宽的柱子
You didn't necessarily program it to have pillars that were two tiles wide,
但这只是随机化的本质--这就是你得到的
but just the nature of randomization-- that's just what you get.
这是程序级生成的另一个令人兴奋的事情
And that's another exciting thing about procedural level generation
它甚至可以让编写算法的人感到惊讶
is that it can surprise even the person that wrote the algorithm.
这真的很酷 而且它省去了你必须创建关卡的工作
It's really cool, and it saves you work having to create levels.
这就是柱子水平
So that was pillared levels.
鸿沟级别--谁能告诉我我们如何才能计算出鸿沟级别？
Chasm levels-- who can tell me how we can do chasm levels?
观众：你只要跳过一栏即可
AUDIENCE: You just skip a column.
科尔顿·奥格登：是的
COLTON OGDEN: Yep.
您可以跳过一列
you skip a column.
所以一开始 我们基本上只能说
So at the very beginning, all we can just basically say
是 我想在这里制造一个鸿沟吗？
is, do I want to generate a chasm here?
如果我这样做了 就跳过
If I do, just skip.
转到循环的下一个迭代
Go to the next iteration of the loop.
所以我们来看看这一点
And so we'll take a look at that.
就这么简单 因为Lua没有继续的概念--
As simple as it is, because Lua doesn't have the notion of continue--
这将是一次重温 因为我相信
this will be a refresher, because I believe
这是在其中一个作业中--
this was in one of the assignments--
它有一份Goto声明
it has a goto statement.
因此 基本上 代码与前面一样 逐列开始
So basically, same code as before, starting column by column.
在贴图宽度之前 X等于1
x equals one until map width.
我们有七分之一的机会--
We have a 1 in 7 chance--
太武断了
just arbitrary.
理想情况下 这应该是--
And this should ideally--
如果您正在设计一个完整的大型游戏或应用程序
if you're engineering an entire large game or application,
这可能会被称为spawn_chasm_Chance
this would be called SPAWN_CHASM_CHANCE probably,
然后在某个地方将其设置为7
and just set that to seven somewhere.
但我们这里只是把它设为7--
But we're just setting it to 7 here--
只是一个静态的幻数 但幻数通常是不好的
just a static magic number, but magic numbers are generally bad.
继续--所以继续在循环的最底部
Goto continue-- and so continue is here at the very bottom of the loop
这就是x=1的mapWidth
here, which is this for x = 1, mapWidth.
所以它会有直接跳到x等于2的效果 如果这是1
So it will have the effect of skipping straight to x equals 2 if this at 1,
例如
for example.
许多语言只是简单地延续了下去
A lot of languages just simply have continue.
Lua没有继续 所以这是社区建立的传统
Lua does not have continue, so this is a community established tradition
用于在Lua中实现类似于Continue的行为
for implementing continue-like behavior in Lua.
您通过双冒号创建一个标签 该标签带有一个名称 然后是一个双冒号
You create a label via double colon with a name and then a double colon,
然后你就直接去找它
and then you just goto it.
这就像产生裂缝一样简单
And so that's as simple as it is for generating chasms.
所以 如果我们到第二级运行 我们就会得到裂缝
And so if we go to level2 and run that, we get chasms.
所以现在我们有了一点有趣的视觉变化
And so now we've got a little bit of interesting visual variety.
在这个例子中 它并没有产生大量的裂缝
It's not spawning a ton of chasms in this example.
到目前为止 它已经产生了一个
It spawned one so far.
还有一个
There's another one.
有时只是紧急情况下 你可以得到两个
And then sometimes just emergently, you can get two.
看 这就对了
See, there we go.
结果 我们遇到了一些有趣的障碍
We get some interesting obstacles as a result.
看起来就像是有人故意这么做的--
It almost looks as if someone intentionally did that--
差不多了
almost.
我可能会 就像我说的 把柱子的尺寸缩小一点
I would probably, like I said, shrink the pillar size a little bit.
它有点高
It's a little tall.
就是这样
That's that.
这是基本的程序--在平台的背景下
That's basic procedural-- in the context of platformers,
这就是我们如何开始的心理模型
that's the mental model for how we can start
想着制造障碍
thinking about generating obstacles.
你可以选择很多不同的方向
And there's a lot of different directions you could go.
比方说 也许你想要建造金字塔
Let's say maybe you wanted to generate pyramids.
我是说 这在马里奥很常见
I mean, it's a common thing in Mario.
将有步骤 [INAUDIBLE]为它设置
There will be steps, [INAUDIBLE] set for it.
同样的实现基本上也会在这里发生
The same implementation would basically happen here.
会有一点不同 因为你是
It would be a little bit different, because you're
在逐列的基础上这样做
doing it on a column by column basis.
但你只需要有效地保持一个引用
But you'd effectively just maintain a reference
到类似台阶的高度 然后你
to something like step height, and then you
会说生成楼梯在这里是正确的
would say generate stairs is true here.
然后您只需将Step Height设置为1
And then you would just set step height to 1.
然后你在这里添加一块瓷砖
So then you add a tile here.
你可以从地面一直到台阶高度 生成一块瓷砖
You would go from ground level up until step height, generate a tile,
转到下一步 然后将步高增加到2
go the next one, and then increment step height to 2.
然后从地面开始 直到台阶的高度--
And then do from ground until step height--
瓷砖会往上爬
tiles go up.
然后是1 然后是2和3 直到达到楼梯宽度 在这种情况下
So 1 and then 2 and 3 until you've gone to stairs width, in which case
您将停止生成楼梯
you stop generating stairs.
这就是你如何
That's this principle behind how you could
做一些稍微复杂一点的事情
do something a little more complicated.
或者金字塔--同样的东西 金字塔的宽度
Or pyramids-- same exact thing, pyramid width.
然后你一直走到金字塔的宽度等于--
And then you just go until pyramid width equals--
或者我们在金字塔宽度除以2 让它向上
or we're at pyramid width divided by 2, make it go up.
如果我们比它高 就让它降下来
And if we're higher than that, make it go down.
然后你就会得到金字塔方法的影响
And then you have the effect of the pyramid approach.
嗯
Yeah.
观众：你们把栏目放在哪里？
AUDIENCE: Where are you putting the column
如果它是[INAUDIBLE] 则生成
generation if it's a [INAUDIBLE].
它没有处于播放状态
It's not in the play state.
科尔顿·奥格登：在这种情况下 一切都在主线上 卢阿
COLTON OGDEN: In this case, it's all in main.lua.
但在发行版中 它将位于Level Maker.lua中
But in the distro, it's going to be in levelmaker.lua.
所以我们已经突破了所有这些功能
So we've broken out all of this functionality
我们是如何越狱的
into just how we did Breakout.
我们有同样的东西--水平制造者--
We had the same sort of thing-- level maker--
它只有LevMaker.Generate
and it just has levelMaker.generate.
然后你给它一个宽度和高度
And then you give it a width and a height,
它将为你生成一个完整的关卡
and it will generate an entire level for you.
观众：整个级别 但它必须持续--
AUDIENCE: An entire level, but it has to continuously--
哦 你一下子把它都生成了？
oh, you generate it all at once?
它不会在你走路时产生吗？
It doesn't generate as you walk?
科尔顿·奥格登：问题是 它是持续产生的 还是一次性产生的？
COLTON OGDEN: The question is, does it generate continuously or all at once?
它只是一下子产生所有的东西
It just generates all at once.
所以你可以实施一个--
So you could implement a--
如果你想成为一名无限长跑运动员 你会选择你自己
if you wanted to do an infinite runner, the way you would do that is you
会把你的关卡分成小块
would break up your level into chunks.
而对于无限的跑步者 通常你只能朝一个方向移动
And with infinite runners, usually you can only move in one direction.
所以当你向右转时 你之前产生的水平--他们得到
So as you go right, your levels that you've generated before-- they get
丢弃 因此您可以避免内存过度消耗
discarded, so you avoid memory overconsumption.
你要做的就是生成一大块--
What you would do is you would just generate a chunk--
也许是100乘20级
maybe a 100 by 20 level.
然后你会经历那个 经历那个
And then you would go through that, through that.
然后当你到达平端时 可能减去5块或10块瓷砖
And then when you get to level end minus maybe like five tiles or 10 tiles,
你会生成另一个 附加它 放在右边
you would generate another one, append it, put it to the right,
然后你就可以从左边转到右边
and then you would just go from the left to the right.
你可能需要一些半花哨的代码
And you probably would need some sort of semi-fancy code
一旦你生成了它们 就把它们拼接在一起
to splice them together once you've generated them.
或者 你可以随时垫上你的--
Alternatively, you could just always pad your--
不 你可能不想垫垫
no, you probably wouldn't want to pad.
我可能会把它们首尾相连 然后去掉x等于1100
I would probably just splice them end to end and then get rid of x equals 1 100
或者 一旦它超过屏幕的左边缘 就会有很多人出现在左侧
or however many on the left once it's gone past the left edge of the screen.
在这种情况下 总而言之 它完全是静态的
In this case, to summarize, it's all static.
但你可以很容易地--
But you could very easily--
这并不容易 但你完全可以让它成为一名无限的跑步者
not easily, but you could very well make it an infinite runner.
嗯
Yeah.
观众：所以我们渲染了整个关卡 但我们就是看不到全部？
AUDIENCE: So we're rendering the entire level, but we just can't see it all?
科尔顿·奥格登：问题是 我们是在渲染整个关卡吗
COLTON OGDEN: The question is, are we rendering the entire level,
但我们就是看不到一切吗？
but we just can't see it all?
答案是肯定的
The answer is yes.
目前 在这个实现中 我们只是渲染整个级别--
Currently, in this implementation, we're just rendering the entire level--
因此 一块一块地被吸引到屏幕上
so tile by tile is getting drawn to the screen.
对于像这样的小例子来说 这不是一个问题
For small examples like this, it's not a concern.
但对于较大的级别--例如 如果我们做一个Terraria级别
But for a large level-- like if we did a Terraria level, for example.
兵马俑数以千计的瓷砖可能
Terraria's thousands and thousands of tiles wide by probably
1000或更高的瓷砖--
1,000 or more tiles tall--
您只想渲染一块 只渲染您可以看到的部分
you want to render only a chunk, only what you can visibly see.
为此 您可以使用相机偏移量 然后只需渲染
And for that, you could use your camera offset and then just render
从左侧的一块瓷砖到底部边缘以下的一块瓷砖
from one tile to the left and above that to one tile below the bottom edge
在摄像机的右手边
of the camera and to the right of it.
只需渲染该分片的子集
Just render that subset of tiles.
因此 您只需要一个for循环来迭代一小段
So you just need a for loop to iterate over a small section.
观众：所以你可以做一个阵列
AUDIENCE: So you can kind of make an array
地图会是什么样子 然后
of what the map's going to look like and then
只渲染数组中您可以看到的部分
just render only slices of the array that you can see.
是那么回事吗？
Is that right?
如果您放置一个多维数组 然后您只需遍历它
If you put a multi-dimensional array and then you just go through it
并随时随地渲染--这就是你的想法吗？
and render as you go-- is that the thought?
科尔顿·奥格登：问题是 你只要
COLTON OGDEN: Question was, you just have
针对您的关卡的多维瓷砖阵列
a multi-dimensional array of tiles for your level,
然后你只需要在你走的时候渲染它
and then you just render it as you go.
答案是肯定的
The answer is yes.
你会得到你的整体瓷砖--
You would have your overall tiles--
您的大型2D阵列 由100×20或其他数千个瓷砖组成
your big 2D array of 100 by 20 or however many thousands of tiles.
然后根据您的摄像机渲染的位置
And then based on wherever your camera is rendering,
它只是一个嵌套数量内for循环
it's just a for loop within that just of a nested amount.
所以 也许你的玩家在x30加上6张牌
So maybe your player is at x 30 plus 6 tiles.
所以你只需要渲染30块到45块
So you would just render from 30 tiles to maybe 45 tiles
在x上 在y上可能是10到20--
on x and maybe 10 to 20 on the y--
就是那一大块
just that chunk.
这只是相对于你的相机的位置
And it's just relative to where your camera is.
你总是只渲染一小部分--
You're always rendering just a small little--
基本上 在这一点上 它实际上是一个相机
basically, it is effectively a camera at that point.
它正在将一大块瓷砖渲染到屏幕上
It's rendering a chunk of the tiles to the screen.
听众：但在这段代码中 情况并非如此
AUDIENCE: But in this code, it's not.
科尔顿·奥格登：在这段代码中 没有
COLTON OGDEN: In this code, no.
这里的水平是--
The levels here are--
它已经足够复杂了 不能引入
it's sufficiently complicated to introduce.
我的意思是 这并不是太复杂的介绍
I mean, it's not too complicated to introduce.
这很容易
It's pretty easy.
但消费--这里的加工--
But the consumption-- the processing here--
是非常轻的 因为能级相当小
is very light, because the levels are fairly small.
即使我们真的有很大的水平
And even if we did have really large levels,
它足够小 不必担心
it's sufficiently small to not have to worry about it.
但如果我们真的达到了1000块或更多的水平
But if we did get to a point where your levels were 1,000 tiles or more,
然后也许这些瓷砖有额外的
and then maybe those tiles have additional,
你只是想挤出所有可能的性能
you just want to squeeze all the performance possible out
您的应用程序的
of your application.
您可以考虑只渲染一个子集
You could look into just rendering a subset.
它很容易介绍 但就是不能
It's fairly simple to introduce but just not something
我们在这项任务中包含了
that we included in this assignment.
关于这种东西是如何工作的 还有其他问题吗？
Any other questions as to how this sort of thing works?
好的
OK.
到目前为止 我们已经讨论了过程级生成
So far, we've talked about procedural level generation.
我们已经讨论了动画和渲染之类的东西
We've talked about animation and rendering and all that stuff.
我们还没有真正讨论如何做瓷砖碰撞
We haven't really talked about how to do tile collision.
我们不会涉及太多的细节
And we won't go into a terrible amount of detail,
因为代码有点长
because the code is a little lengthy.
阅读并理解它将是你们任务的一部分
It'll be part of your assignment to read over it and understand it,
但我们拥有的是TileMap类
but it's in the TileMap class that we have.
基本上 整个大意是因为我们是
Basically, the whole gist is that because we're
在固定的2D切片数组上 它将始终为0 0 至少
on a 2D tile array that's fixed, it'll always be at 0, 0, at least
在我们目前实现的模型中
in the model that we've currently implemented.
我们只需将坐标转换为平铺 然后
We can just convert coordinates to tiles and then
只要检查一下 看看瓷砖是否在任何地方
just check to see whether or not the tiles at whatever that is
是不是坚固的
are solid or not.
在这种情况下 假设我们想要查看角色的顶部
Let's say we wanted to look at the top of our character in this case.
所以如果我们有我们的角色在这里
So if we have our character here.
为了说明起见 我把他放在他上方的两块瓷砖之间
For the sake of illustration, I put him between two tiles above him
只是为了表明我们为什么需要以我们现在的方式来做这件事
just to show why we need to do this the way that we are doing it.
但你要说的是--
But you take the point here--
他的最左上角 所以是player.x 然后是player.y
his very top left, so player.x and then player.y,
这实际上就是他们的0 0版本
which is effectively their version of 0, 0.
然后是Player.x加上Player.Width减去--
And then player.x plus player.width minus--
对于很多碰撞 我们都是负1
we do a minus one for a lot of collisions
这样他就可以在街区之间走动了
so that he can walk between blocks and stuff like that.
因为如果你不给他稍微少一点的钱--
Because if you don't basically give him slightly less than the amount--
因为他有16个像素宽 瓷砖有16个像素宽--
because he's 16 pixels wide, and the tiles are 16 pixels wide--
如果他在两个街区之间想摔倒
if he's between two blocks and he wanted to fall down,
他只是不会倒下 因为它还在探测碰撞
he just won't fall down, because it's still detecting a collision.
因为如果他在这个洞里--
Because if he's on the hole here--
假设这是一个洞 这些是这里的瓷砖
let's say this is the hole, and these are the tiles here.
X加上宽度--
The x plus the width--
它会在这块瓷砖和这块瓷砖上引发碰撞
it'll trigger a collision on this tile and this tile still.
所以基本上 你需要将他的碰撞框最小化一个像素
So basically, you need to minimize his collision box by one pixel
从本质上讲 要适应16个像素的间隙 这就是它的归结
to fit through 16 pixel gaps essentially is what it boils down to.
但碰撞背后的主旨--
But the gist behind collision--
在这种情况下 这只适用于他
in this case, this would only apply when he's
跳跃 因为这是他唯一能真正
jumping, because this is the only time at which he can really
与他上方的瓷砖相撞
collide with tiles that are above him.
您将测试落在此像素上的任何块
You would test for whatever block falls on this pixel
不管落在这个像素上的是什么块
and whatever block falls on this pixel.
如果它们中的任何一个是实心的 就会引发碰撞
And if either of them are solid, you trigger collision.
如果没有 那么根本就不会发生碰撞
And if not, then there's no collision at all.
例如 如果他就在这里--
So if he's right here, for example--
就在瓷砖的正下方--它只会检查一个瓷砖
right directly beneath a tile-- it's only going to check one tile.
这一点和这一点都将落在这块瓷砖上
This point and this point are both going to fall on this tile.
但我们之所以要检查这里和这里的两个点
But the reason that we want to check for both points here and here
如果他在两块不同的瓷砖下面
is in the event that he is beneath two separate tiles,
因为现在这一点将检查这块瓷砖
because now this point's going to check this tile,
这一块将检查这块瓷砖
and this one's going to check this tile.
我们不能只检查这个瓷砖 因为如果我们只检查这个瓷砖
We can't just check this tile, because if we only check this tile
这里没有瓷砖 但这里有瓷砖
and there was no tile here but there was a tile here,
他的跳跃仍然不会引发碰撞
him jumping would still not trigger a collision.
它会认为它只是在看这里 而不是这里
It would think that it was only looking here and not here.
所以对于我们有效地在他的每一边进行的每一次碰撞
So for every collision on every side we do of him effectively,
我们需要有效地检查那条边的两个角
we need to check both corners of that edge effectively.
所以当他跳的时候 我们转到这一点--
So when he's jumping, we turn this point--
这个x y--只需除以瓷砖的大小就可以得到瓷砖
this x, y-- into a tile by just dividing it by tile size.
所以我们可以说 Player.x除以瓷砖大小加1
So we can say, player.x divided by tile size plus one.
这将等于x上的任何平铺
That's going to equal whatever tile this is on the x.
然后对y做同样的事情--
And then same thing for the y--
我们只需将y除以瓷砖大小 然后在上面加1
we just divide the y by tile size, and then we add 1 to it.
这将使我们能够得到准确的瓷砖
And that will allow us to get the exact tile.
如果我们使用从操作中得到的x y
If we use those x, y that we get from that operation,
我们有效地获得了瓦片2D数组中y x索引处的精确瓦片
we get the exact tile at that y, x index in our tile's 2D array effectively.
所以我们对跳跃也是这样做的
So we do that for jump.
我们检查了他头顶的两个角
We check both corners of the top of his head.
我们对底部做同样的事情 只是在那个时候
We do the same thing for the bottom, only at that time,
我们检查x 然后y加上高度
we're checking x, and then y plus height,
然后x加上宽度 y加上高度
and then x plus width, y plus height.
如果我们做的是左边缘 我们要检查什么？
And then if we're doing the left edge, what are we checking?
观众：左下角和左上角？
AUDIENCE: The bottom left and top left?
科尔顿·奥格登：我们是
COLTON OGDEN: We are.
所以这将是x0 y 然后是x0 y加上高度
So that will be x0, y, and then x0, y plus height.
然后如果它是正确的边缘 同样的事情
And then if it's the right edge, same thing.
我们检查x+宽度y 然后我们检查x+宽度y+高度
We check x plus width y, and then we check x plus width y plus height.
这就是这个发行版中碰撞检测背后的主旨
And so that's the gist behind collision detection in the distro here.
如果我们转到磁贴地图 你可以在马里奥看到它
And you can see it in Mario if we go to TileMap.
指向磁贴--这实际上就是它发生的地方
Point to tile-- this is effectively where it happens.
在第32行 我们基本上是返回--
On line 32, we're basically returning--
这里的这段代码--
this bit of code here--
28比30--是一张支票
28 to 30-- is a check.
因为我们可以跳过地图的边缘 我们
Because we can jump over the map edge, we
将无法在切片y除以平铺大小时进行检查
won't be able to check at tile y divided by TILE_SIZE
加1 x除以平铺大小加1 因为这些都是零
plus 1, x divided by TILE_SIZE plus one, because those will be nil.
这些都不会存在 因为他真的会
Those won't exist, because he'll literally
在地图边界之外
be outside the map boundaries.
如果他在它下面 或者他超过了左边或右边 情况也是一样的
Same thing if he goes below it or he goes beyond the left or right edge.
这就是这里的所有代码
So that's all this code is here.
它只是确保如果我们真的超越地图的边界
It just makes sure that if we do go beyond the map boundaries,
我们归零
we return nil.
因此 我们可以检查为零 而不是得到瓷砖索引错误
So that way, we can check nil rather than getting a tile index error.
然后在第32行是我刚才提到的操作
And then on line 32 is the operation that I just mentioned,
那就是我们用y--
which was we take the y--
所以我们传入的这个x和y将是玩家的实际x y
so this x and y that we pass in are going to be the player's actual x, y.
当我们传递这些信息时 我们只需要在self上获得瓷砖 瓷砖
When we pass those in, we're just going to get the tile at self.tiles,
然后有效地y除以Tile_Size得到一个整数
and then effectively y divided by TILE_SIZE taken down to an integer,
然后加1
and then add 1.
回想一下 表是1索引的 但坐标是0索引的
Because recall, tables are 1 indexed, but the coordinates are 0 indexed.
因此 这将导致索引结果为0 因此我们希望将其加1
So this will result in a 0 indexed outcome, so we want to add 1 to it.
这里的情况也一样--math.loor(X)除以TableSize加1
Same thing for here-- math.floor(x) divided by TILE_SIZE plus 1.
因此 有效地 指向瓷砖
So effectively, points to tiles.
然后我们就从那里得到一块瓷砖
And then we'll just get a tile from that.
而瓷砖--我们可以检查一下 嘿 那瓷砖是不是实心的？
And the tile-- we can just check, hey, is that tile solid or not?
如果是 则触发碰撞
If it is, trigger collision.
这就是能够在平台上做到这一点的主旨
So that's the gist behind being able to do it in a platformer
在那里一切都是固定的
where everything is fixed.
这就像是我们可以走的一条捷径
That's sort of like a shortcut we can take.
因为现在 这有什么好处呢？
Because now, what's the nice thing about this?
这个算法有一个非常棒的地方
What jumps out as being a super nice thing about this algorithm,
想象一下 我们的游戏世界里有10,000块瓷砖
imagining that we have, let's say, 10,000 tiles in our game world.
所以如果你看一看 我们所做的就是
So if you look and see, all we're doing is
我们只是在做一个简单的数学运算
we're just doing a simple mathematical operation
关于他的x和y是什么 对吗？
on what his x and y is, right?
除了这个 还有什么办法？
What's the alternative to this?
例如 如果我们通过AABB进行这项工作
If we were doing this via AABB, for example,
我们必须遍历每一块瓷砖 对吗？
we'd have to iterate over every single tile, right?
观众：你能总结一下吗？
AUDIENCE: Can you summarize?
为了避免重复屏幕上的所有内容
To avoid iterating over everything on the screen,
你只是检查了他所在的栏目和栏目标题？
you just check the column that he's in and the column tile?
科尔顿·奥格登：是的
COLTON OGDEN: Yep.
所以大意是他有一个x和一个y
So the gist is he's got an x and a y.
X和y将在世界坐标中 所以他的x可能是67
The x and the y are going to be in world coordinates, so his x could be 67
他的y可能是38岁左右
and his y could be 38 or something like that.
它们不会均匀地映射到瓷砖
They don't map evenly to tiles.
但如果我们把这些除以我们世界中的瓷砖大小--
But if we divide those by whatever the tile size is in our world--
16--这将是一模一样的瓷砖
16-- that's going to be the exact tile.
我们还必须在它的基础上加1 因为Lua中的表是1索引的
We also have to add 1 to it, because the tables in lua are 1 indexed.
但是我们可以用x y来索引我们自己的瓷砖
But we can index our self.tiles at the x, y
我们从中得到的--除以16
that we get from that-- the dividing by 16.
这就是他要撞上的瓷砖
And that will be the exact tile that he's colliding with.
我们基本上不需要有一系列的瓷砖
We don't have to basically have a collection of tiles
我们迭代并检查它们是否
that we iterate over and check whether they
使用AABB碰撞检测与玩家碰撞
collide with the player using AABB collision detection
就像我们以前做过的那样
like we've done before.
因为回想一下 在《越狱》中 我们有砖头 对吗？
Because recall, in Breakout, we had the bricks, right?
他们都有自己的x y 但他们不在一个网格上
They all had their own x, y, but they weren't on a grid.
他们还没修好
They weren't fixed.
所以我们不得不真的把它们拿来做AABB
So we had to actually take them and do an AABB.
我们不得不迭代它们并对它们执行AABB
We had to iterate over them and perform AABB on them,
因为没有确定性的方法可以非常快速地对它们进行索引
because there's no deterministic way to just index at them really quickly.
数组和链表的情况是一样的
It's the same thing with arrays versus linked lists.
因为数组--你可以计算某个值在多大程度上被赋予了索引
Because arrays-- you can calculate how far some value is given an index.
您可以立即访问它
You have instant access to it.
这是一个操作的顺序 而不是链表
It's an order of one operation as opposed to a linked list.
如果你想试着得到一个特定值
If you want to try and get to a particular value,
你必须遍历整个过程 直到找到它
you have to iterate through the entire thing until you find it.
观众：你能不能找一下你可能要降落的栏目？
AUDIENCE: Can you just look for the column that you might be landing on?
科尔顿·奥格登：无论你的x除以16 你都能得到准确的瓷砖--
COLTON OGDEN: You're getting the exact tile at whatever your x divided by 16--
或者不管你的瓷砖大小是什么--
or whatever your tile size is--
你的y除以16是
and your y divided by 16 is.
记住 你这么做是为了两个不同的观点
And you're doing it, recall, for two different points
取决于你要找的是什么
depending on what you're looking for.
如果你要找的是高于你角色的瓷砖
If you're looking for the tiles that are above your character,
你将在这一点上做这件事
you're going to be doing it for this point.
所以不管这个值是什么--他的基数x y-
So whatever this value is-- his base x, y--
不管它被16除以什么 然后再除以16
whatever that is divided by 16 and then whatever that is divided by 16.
然后你就可以得到他正上方的瓷砖了
And then that'll get you whatever tiles are directly above him.
它将与与该点相交的任何切片相交
It will intersect with whatever tile intersects with this point
任何瓷砖都与这一点相交
and whatever tile intersects with this point.
如果我们看左边 这里和这里也是一样的
Same thing with here and here if we're looking on the left,
这里 这里 如果我们看的是底部
here, here if we're looking on the bottom,
这里和这里 如果我们看的是右边的话
and here and here if we're looking on the right side.
我们会在他已经
And we check for collision after he's already
移动以使这些点与可能的块相交
moved so that these points will be intersected with potential blocks.
这就是我们可以检查是否发生碰撞的方法
And that's how we can check whether it's a collision or not.
我们在他移动和处于某种移动状态时这样做
We do this when he moves and is in some sort of movement state.
观众：所以你还在做碰撞检测
AUDIENCE: So you're still doing collision detection
他的实际坐标 但你只是
with his actual coordinates, but you're just
缩小你的字符宽度--
narrowing what you're character width--
科尔顿·奥格登：是的
COLTON OGDEN: Yep.
我们把它从在每一块瓷砖上迭代
we're turning it from iterating over every single tile
到即时运算 因为我们可以从数学上得到
to an instant operation, because we can just mathematically get
一模一样的瓦片 他没有
the exact tiles that he's at without having
担心他在地图上的位置
to worry about where he is in the map.
这只是即时访问
It's just instant access.
这只是因为我们知道瓷砖总是
And this only works because we know the tiles are always
固定在完全相同的位置
fixed in the exact same locations.
他们总是从0 0开始
They're always starting at 0, 0.
它们永远都是瓷砖大小
They're always going to be TILE_SIZE.
当事情变得更复杂的时候
Things get a little more complicated when
我们引入游戏对象 它们有自己独立的x y
we introduce game objects, which have their own independent x, y.
对于这些 您确实需要迭代
And for those, you do have to iterate over.
基本上 您拥有一组游戏对象或一组实体
You have basically a collection of game objects or a collection of entities.
让我们假设游戏世界里有蜗牛
Let's say we have snails in the game world.
蜗牛不会每次都出现在某个固定的位置
The snails aren't going to be at some fixed location every time.
它们可以连续移动
They can move continuously.
因此 对于这些 我们必须将它们全部保存在一个容器中
So for those, we have to actually keep them all in a container
然后循环浏览它们 然后说 我的球员有没有撞到其中的任何一个？
and then loop through them and say, has my player collided with any of these?
如果他有 那么就会引发与那只蜗牛的碰撞--
If he has, then trigger a collision with that snail--
如果玩家处于行走状态或跳跃状态 则杀死它或杀死该玩家
kill it or kill the player if he's in a walking state or a jump state.
如果他处于跌倒状态 那么他们
And if he's in a falling state, then they
应该会死 因为他正从顶部与他们相撞
should die, because he's colliding with them from the top.
然后缩小检查碰撞的范围 就像你在底部看到的那样
And you narrow down what collision you check for, as you can see at the bottom
这里
here.
瓷砖碰撞--当你看着你的角色上方时
Tile collision-- when you're looking above your character,
你只是在测试当你处于跳跃状态时
you're only testing that when you're in the jumping state,
因为这是你唯一需要的时间
because it's the only time you need to.
所以这是唯一一个你会与你上方的瓷砖相撞的点
So that's the only point at which you'll collide with tiles that are above you.
当你处于下落状态时 你就会检查你脚下的瓷砖
When you're in the falling state is when you'll check for tiles below you.
然后你可以与你身边的瓷砖互动
And then you can interact with tiles to your side
当你处于跳跃、坠落或移动状态时
when you're in either the jumping, falling, or moving state,
因此 您应该检查所有这三个州的左侧和右侧磁贴
so you should check for left and right tiles in all three of those states.
观众：你不是应该总是测试一下自己的底线 以防出现裂痕吗？
AUDIENCE: Shouldn't you always test for beneath you in case you get a chasm?
科尔顿·奥格登：以防万一？
COLTON OGDEN: In case what?
观众：以防出现裂痕
AUDIENCE: In case you get a chasm.
科尔顿·奥格登：如果你有裂痕 是的
COLTON OGDEN: In case you get chasm, yes.
你说得对
You're correct.
这实际上应该只在播放器中进行测试
This should actually be tested only when in the player
跌倒状态和球员行走状态 是的
falling state and player walking state, yes.
所以问题是 你不是应该测试你脚下的瓷砖吗
So the question was, shouldn't you be testing for tiles beneath you
当你走路的时候？
when you're walking?
是的--不仅是摔倒 而且还会走路
And yes-- not just falling, but walking as well.
这只只会跳 这只会摔倒 还会走路
This one only jumping, this one falling and walking,
这个是跳跃、坠落和移动的
and this one for jumping, falling, and moving.
这有意义吗--
Does that make sense--
我们如何将x y转化为一块瓷砖
how we can take the x, y and sort of turn that into a tile
只要除以16就行了吗？
by just dividing it by 16?
而且一定要注意加1 因为我们自己的瓷砖 瓷砖
And do note the plus 1 as well, because our tiles in our self.tiles
有1个索引
are 1 indexed.
所以当我们用x y除以瓷砖大小时 我们就是
And so when we divide x, y by tile size, we're
将得到一个0索引坐标
going to get a 0 indexed coordinate.
如果我们的x是14 我们就在第一个瓦片内
If our x is at 14, we're within the first tile.
但如果我们把它除以16 我们会得到零
But if we divide that by 16, we're going to get zero.
所以我们需要加1 这样我们就得到了数组中的第一个平铺
So we need to add 1 to that so that we get the first tile in the array
不管那块瓷砖是什么 它都会是
still, which will be whatever that tile is.
这就是碰撞的原理
So that's how the collision works.
它都是在这里的TileMap中实现的
It's all implemented in TileMap here.
基本上玩家所处的每一个状态 都在StatesEntity中
And basically every state that the player is in, which is in StatesEntity,
然后运动员跌倒 无所事事 跳跃和行走--
and then player falling, idle, jump, and walking--
这些都是执行此检查的状态
these are all states that perform this check.
他们基本上做了这里的所有逻辑
They basically do all the logic that's here
在底部 这是在播放器中测试
at the bottom, which is testing in the player
左碰撞或右碰撞的跳跃状态、下降状态和移动状态
jumping state, falling state, and moving state for left or right collision.
然后在下落状态下 我们检查下面是否有碰撞
And then in the falling state, we check for collision below us.
然后在跳跃状态下 我们检查上方是否有碰撞
And then in jumping state, we check for collision above us.
这一切都是在各州内部完成的
That's all done within the states themselves.
但从像素到瓷砖的实际转换--
But the actual transformation from pixels to tiles--
这只是我们从TileMap调用的一个函数
that's just a function that we call from TileMap.
这只是一个效用函数
It's just a utility function.
观众：这个函数叫什么来着？
AUDIENCE: What's the function called again?
科尔顿·奥格登：这叫PointToTile
COLTON OGDEN: It's called pointToTile.
所以如果你在TileMap的第27行--
So if you're in TileMap on line 27--
PointToTile(x y)
pointToTile(x, y).
这里的第一点只是一小部分
And the first little bit here is just the bit
这基本上可以让你走出地图的界限
that lets you basically go outside the map bounds
而不会出现平铺索引错误
without getting a tile index error.
因此 如果它正好在平铺限制之外 小于0 或大于宽度
So if it's just outside the tile limits, less than 0, or greater than width,
只需返回零即可
just return nil.
所以你可以在nil上做一个检查
And so you can do a check on nil to check
查看TileMap point tToTile是否等于Nil
to see whether TileMap pointToTile is equal to nil
或者当你做碰撞的时候不会
or not when you do the collision.
如果是的话 那就什么都别做了
And if it is, then just don't do anything probably.
但假设您在磁贴边界内 在第32行
But assuming that you're within the tile boundaries, on line 32
就是你进行转化的地方--数学地板 回想一下
is where you do that transformation-- the math.floor, recall,
因为我们想要得到这些的整数值
because we want to get integer values for these.
我们不想得到小数 因为你
We don't want to get fractional numbers, because you
我不能将这些瓷砖作为小数编制索引 尽管我不确定
can't index these tiles as fractional numbers, although I'm not sure.
我认为在Lua中通常可以--为瓷砖建立索引
I think you might be able to in Lua generally-- index a tile
以一个小数
by a fractional number.
但在本例中 我们只需要整数
But in this case, we just want integers.
所以我们将y上的数学地板除以平铺大小加1
So we call math.floor on y divided by TILE_SIZE plus 1,
Y除以平铺大小 然后再加1
y divided by TILE_SIZE then add 1 to that,
然后我们对x做同样的事情
and then we do the same thing for the x.
这就是我们的行动
So that's the operation.
然后在我们想要检查任何我们想要碰撞的瓷砖的地方
And then wherever we want to check for whatever tiles we want to collide for,
我们只在x和y坐标上调用point ToTile
we just call pointToTile on those x and y coordinates.
这就是游戏中所有基于瓷砖的碰撞背后的主干
That's the backbone behind all the tile-based collision in the game
有效地
effectively.
对于这是如何工作的 有什么问题吗？
Any questions as to how this works?
是
Yes.
观众：所以你探测到的只是角落的碰撞
AUDIENCE: So you're only detecting the collision of corners
而不是边缘本身？
and not the edge itself?
科尔顿·奥格登：正确 因为你真的不需要检查边缘
COLTON OGDEN: Correct, because you don't really need to check for the edge
如果考虑到上角和下角
if you're taking into consideration the top and bottom corner,
除非你的实体足够高 他们需要
unless your entity is sufficiently tall that they need
检查是否有三块以上的瓷砖
to check for more than three tiles.
在这种情况下 我们的实体不超过两个瓷砖高
In this case, our entity is not more than two tiles tall,
所以我们只需要检查他的左上角 左下角
so we only need to check for his top left, bottom left.
如果是左碰撞 右上角 右下角
If we're doing a left collision, top right, bottom right.
如果我们在做右碰撞 他的左上角 右上角的顶部和底部
If we're doing a right collision, his top left, top right for top and bottom
左下角 右下角为底部
left, bottom right for bottom.
如果你有一个八块高的实体
If you had an entity that was eight tiles tall,
你需要检查他右侧的每一块瓷砖
you need to check every single tile along his right side, which
只是意味着你需要迭代他的整个身高除以瓷砖大小
just means you need to iterate over his entire height divided by tile size.
然后只需对每个瓷砖检查的y进行偏移
And then just offset the y that you're checking for each of those tiles.
这说得通吗？
Does that makes sense?
好的 酷
OK, cool.
好的
All right.
我通过提到国家简要地提到了这一点
I alluded to this briefly by mentioning state.
我不知道我是否暗示了我们使用实体的事实
I don't know if I alluded so much to the fact that we're using entities.
但在这个发行版中 我们被介绍了实体的概念
But in this distro, we're introduced to the concept of entities.
一个实体几乎可以是你想要的任何东西
An entity can be almost anything you want it to be.
在这个发行版中 我们考虑的是实体
In this distro, we're considering entities
基本上是任何有生命或有知觉的东西--
to basically be anything that's living or sentient moving around--
在这种情况下 球员或蜗牛
in this case, the player or snails.
这些是实体 然后它们只是实体的子集
Those are entities, and then they just are subsets of entity.
实体是一个非常抽象的东西
An entity is a very abstract thing.
你会在很多游戏引擎和很多讨论中看到它
You'll see it in a lot of game engines and a lot of discussions
关于如何组织你的游戏以及如何设计它
about how to organize your game and how to engineer it.
Unity可能是最突出的采用者
Unity is probably the most prominent adopter
所谓的实体组件系统 由此
of what's called the entity component system, whereby
你在你的比赛中拥有一切
you have everything in your game.
你游戏中的每一件事都是一个实体
Every single thing in your game is an entity,
然后每个实体都是由组件组成的
and then every entity is comprised of components.
而这些组件最终会驱动你的行为
And these components ultimately drive your behavior.
这有点像如果你熟悉组合而不是继承
It's sort of like if you're familiar with composition over inheritance.
如果你听说过这是一件软件工程的事情
If you've heard of this as a software engineering thing,
这实际上是相同的范式
that's effectively the same paradigm.
而不是继承一堆不同的东西成为你的--
Rather than inherit a bunch of different things to be your--
假设您有一个基本怪物类
let's say you have a base monster class.
然后你有一个妖精 它是怪物的子集
And then you have a goblin that's a subset of monster,
所以它是从怪物那里继承下来的
so it inherits from monster.
然后你有了一个从小妖精那里继承下来的小妖精军阀
And then you have a goblin warlord who inherits from goblin,
然后你就有了一个从那里继承下来的古老的妖精军阀
and then you have an ancient goblin warlord that inherits from that.
与其让这种嵌套的继承树
Rather than have this nested tree of inheritance,
你采用合成法 这意味着你拿一个底座容器
you adopt composition, which means you take a base container,
然后用不同的组件填充它 这些组件表示
and then you fill it with different components that represent
您的对象的行为是什么
what the behavior of your object is.
所以如果你有一个实体--
So if you have an entity--
比方说 你给它一个怪物组件
let's say you give it a monster component.
然后也许你还会给它一个古老的组成部分
And then maybe you also give it an ancient component,
所以它是一个古老的怪物
so it's an ancient monster.
也许你给它一个妖精组件
And maybe you give it a goblin component,
那么它就是一个古老的妖精
so then it's an ancient monster goblin.
然后你给它一个军阀的组成部分
And then you give it a warlord component,
所以这是一个古老的妖怪军阀
so it's an ancient goblin monster warlord.
所以它包含了构成它的所有部件
So it has all the pieces that make it what
它不需要你去创造这个疯狂的继承链
it is without you having to create this crazy chain of inheritance.
这实际上就是实体组件系统的模型
That's effectively what the model of an entity component system
是与标准继承的对比--用它来驱动
is versus standard inheritance-- using that to drive
你的问题的模型
the model of your problem.
在这种情况下 我们不会讨论疯狂的实体组件
In this case, we're not going into crazy entity components.
但我想提出来 因为团结
But I wanted to bring it up, because Unity,
我们将在几周内介绍 它完全是基于组件的
which we'll be covering in a few weeks, is entirely component-based.
您在Unity中编写的所有内容都是一个组件
Everything you write in Unity is a component.
和实体 无论它们是否在实体组件系统中
And entities, whether they're in an entity component system or not,
构成了大多数大型比赛的中坚力量
form the backbone of most large games.
大多数游戏都有一定的复杂性
Most games that have some complexity to them
将它们中的大多数部分建模为具有行为的实体
model most of the pieces within them as entities that have behaviors
做一些事情
and do things.
因此 在这种情况下 实体是蜗牛和我们的玩家
And so in this case, entities are snails and our player.
然后从瓷砖上分开--
And then separate from the tiles--
当我们做碰撞的时候--
when we do collision for that--
我们还想检查与玩家在每个实体上的冲突
we want to also check collision on every entity with the player.
所以我们要确定在这种情况下玩家与蜗牛相撞
So we make sure that the player's collided with the snail in this case,
因为这是他们唯一可以成为的其他实体
because that's the only other entities that they can be.
但如果你愿意 你可以拥有任意数量的敌人
But you can have an arbitrary number of enemies if you want to.
如果你与一个实体发生冲突--所以只是一个for循环
If you collide with an entity-- so just a for loop.
因此 对于成对的实体 请检查冲突
So for entity in pairs of entities, check collision.
如果你处于跳跃状态 那就去死吧
If you're in the jump state, then die.
如果你处于秋天状态 那就杀了它 等等
If you're in the fall state, kill it, et cetera.
当你在做实体到实体交互的大部分事情时
When you're doing most of your entity to entity interaction stuff,
这通常是您建模的方式
that's generally how you'll model it.
您只需迭代所有内容 然后将所有内容碰撞
You'll just iterate over everything and then just collide everything.
根据什么与什么发生冲突 您将
Depending on what collides with what, you'll
只是将所有东西与其他东西碰撞 并以这种方式处理互动
just collide everything with everything else and process interactions that way.
这是我们有效地做到这一点的方式
That's effectively how we do it.
我们在--
We have in the--
我相信它在GameLevel
I believe it's in GameLevel.
这维护了对充满实体的表的引用
This maintains a reference to a table full of entities,
摆满了物品的桌子
a table full of objects.
物体可以--我们稍后会讨论这一点--
Objects can be-- we'll talk about that in a second--
宝石 积木 灌木丛 诸如此类的东西 然后是一张瓷砖地图
gems, and blocks, and bushes, and stuff like that, and then a tile map.
对于每个实体 我们只需更新它
For every entity, we just update it.
然后对于每个对象 我们都会更新它
And then for every object, we update it.
然后 对于对象中的每个对象 我们也进行渲染
And then for every object in objects, we render it as well.
然后我们渲染每一个实体
And then we render every entity.
这只是你如何看待游戏世界的基本方式
This is just sort of basic how you would take a game world,
填充它 然后处理和更新它
populate it, and then process and update it.
只是容器 维护着对所有东西的引用的表
Just containers, tables that maintain a bunch of references to everything,
然后只需更新它们
and then just update them.
实际的互动发生在--
The actual interaction takes place in the--
因为它们取决于我们所处的状态
because they're dependent on what state we're in.
如果你看一下球员在状态斜杠中的所有不同状态
If you look at all the different states for the player in the states slash
Entity文件夹 您将看到 例如 在玩家倒下状态的第62行
entity folder, you'll see, for example, on line 62 of the player falling state,
我们正在迭代Level中的每个对象
we're iterating over every object in the level.objects.
注意玩家有一个关于它的等级的参考
And notice the player has a reference to its level
这样它就可以访问它里面的所有东西
so that it can access everything within it.
然后在该级别内 所有对象都被存储
And then within that level, all the objects are stored.
所以它所需要做的就是说 如果物体碰撞
So all it needs to do is just say, if the object collides
玩家和对象是实心的 然后将我们的dy设置为零
the player and the object is solid, then set our dy to zero,
等等 等等
et cetera, et cetera.
所有这些代码实际上都很容易阅读
All this code's actually pretty easy to read through,
所以我鼓励你们去看看它
so I would encourage you to take a look at it
只需理解所有的碰撞和东西是如何
and just understand how all the collision and stuff is
在球员、物体、积木和诸如此类的东西之间工作--
working between the player, the objects, the blocks, and things like that--
像积木这样的东西是固体的 像灌木丛这样的东西不是固体
things like blocks are solid, things like bushes are not solid.
但这就是要点
But that's the gist.
拥有对象或实体的集合
Have a collection of objects or entities.
然后根据你所处的状态 与一些
And then depending on what state you're in, collide with some.
然后根据州的情况 也许这会让你丧命
And then depending on the state, maybe that kills you,
也许那会杀死敌人 也许什么都不会发生
maybe that kills the enemy, maybe nothing happens,
也许你变得所向披靡
maybe you become invincible.
也许你撞上了一个通电的游戏物体
Maybe you collide with a power-up game object,
而这种动力触发了你自己 玩家 无敌是真的
and that power-up triggers your self.player.invincible is true.
然后如果self.player.incelble是真的
And then if self.player.invincible is true,
然后 也许你可以用彩虹动画来渲染他
then maybe you render him with a rainbow animation.
然后在任何他会与敌人相撞并死亡的活动中
And then in any of the functions where he would collide and die with an enemy,
他不再死了 他只是杀了他们
he no longer dies, he just kills them.
这就是你如何与物体互动的主旨
So that's sort of the gist behind how you would interact with objects
以及如何处理它
and how to process it.
游戏对象不同
Game objects are different.
就像我之前说的 这些是我们可以看到的一些物体的例子
Like I said earlier, these are examples of some of the objects here we can see.
左下角的宝石都在发行版中
The gems on the bottom left there are all in the distro.
如果你碰到一个街区--如果我们有几分钟的时间
If you hit a block-- and if we have a few minutes,
我会很快地展示给你们看它是怎么工作的--
I'll show you really quickly how that works--
如果你击中一个格挡 你将有机会产生一个宝石
if you hit a block, you'll have a chance to spawn a gem.
如果你收集了gen--也就是说如果你与那个游戏物体相撞--
If you collect the gen-- which means if you collide with that game object--
把你的分数加100
increment your score 100.
这些都是我没有时间实现的其他对象
These are all other objects that I didn't have any time to implement.
但就在大门口 只是作为一个心理练习
But just off the gate, just as a mental exercise,
你觉得我们该怎么做梯子
how do you think we could implement a ladder?
是啊
Yeah.
观众：你只会有一个攀登状态
AUDIENCE: You would just have a climb state.
如果玩家触摸梯子并按下某个键
And if the player is touching a ladder and presses a certain key,
它们会进入爬升状态 这会使它们上升
they would enter the climb state, and that would cause them to go up.
科尔顿·奥格登：正确
COLTON OGDEN: Correct.
托尼说如果他们爬上梯子
So what Tony said was if they go onto a ladder,
它们应该进入爬升状态
they should go into a climb state.
取决于它们是否处于爬升状态
And depending on whether they're in a climb state
如果他们按下一个按钮 他们应该上升或下降
or not, if they press a button, they should go up or down.
然后你会检查
And then you would check.
如果他们在梯子的顶端 离开攀登状态
If they're at the top of the ladder, get off the climb state,
进入步行状态
go into a walk state.
或者如果他们在梯子的底部 进入步行状态
Or if they're at the bottom of the ladder, go into a walk state.
这只是另一个游戏对象 你只是碰撞
And that's just another game object that you just collide with,
对你来说这是一个新的状态
and then it's a new state for you.
是的
Yes.
观众：你可能真的想让它处于一个秋天的状态
AUDIENCE: You may actually want it in a fall state,
因为这样你就可以有一个梯子 实际上不去任何地方
because that way you could have a ladder that doesn't actually go anywhere,
只会让你更高
it just gives you height.
但你可以用它来跳过宽的缝隙
But you could use that to jump over wide gaps.
科尔顿·奥格登：托尼说你可以
COLTON OGDEN: What Tony said was you could
有能力从梯子上跳下来
have the ability to jump off a ladder.
你是这么说的吗是的.
Is that what you Said Yeah.
从梯子上跳下来的能力 这样你就可以把它当作障碍物
The ability to jump off a ladder so that you can then use it as an obstacle.
这是绝对正确的
That's absolutely true.
实际上 我们在这里看到的模型 很难看出来
Actually, in the mock up that we saw up here, it's super hard to see.
我看看能不能放大
I'll see if I can maybe zoom in on it here.
马里奥 马里奥 图形 然后它被称为全张
Mario, Mario, graphics, and then it's called full sheet.
我在这堂课中使用的整个工作表都被称为fullsheet.png
The whole entire sheet that I used for this lecture is called fullsheet.png.
我不知道那是什么
I don't know what that is.
所以如果你把这里放大很高 我们可以有效地看到
So if you zoom in really high here, we can see effectively
你所指的是--
what you were alluding to--
就在这里 这个小小的绳索
right here, this little rope thing.
我猜为了这个模型的缘故
I'm guessing for the sake of this mock up that's
他们想要说明的是
what they were trying to illustrate.
但是你有一个游戏对象 可以让你进入攀登状态
But you have a game object that lets you go into a climb state.
不管它是梯子还是绳子
Whether it's a ladder or whether it's a rope,
只需为玩家添加一个新状态
just add a new state for the player.
如果他们处于攀爬状态 那么我们就有了这个新的动画
If they're in that climb state, then we have this new animation
这是我们之前在床单上看到的 这是他们的背面或正面
which we saw in the sheet earlier, which was their back or their front.
然后他们只是爬上它 然后更新它
And then they just climb up it and just update it
如果他们在梯子上向上或向下移动
if they're moving up or down the ladder.
然后给他们跳下来的能力
And then just give them the ability to jump off.
然后 当你到达顶端或底部时 就下车
And then when you get to the top or bottom, just get off.
你可以想到很多同样的事情 有很多这样的障碍
And you could think a lot of the same thing with a lot of these obstacles,
就像这里的尖刺
like the spikes here.
如果你在跳跃 你击中了它 你可能会死
If you're jumping and you hit it, you should probably die.
因此 您将检查对象ID是否可能等于Spikes
And so you would check for if the object.ID maybe is equal to spikes
或者是否反对致命等于真
or whether object.lethal equals true.
这个也是一样的
Same thing with this one.
然后有些障碍完全是表面上的 就像这里的蘑菇
And then some obstacles are completely cosmetic, like this mushroom here.
就发行版而言 灌木丛、蘑菇和仙人掌
In the case of the distro, bushes and mushrooms and cacti
所有这些东西都完全是表面上的
and all those sorts of things are just completely cosmetic,
这样你就可以穿行其中了
so you can walk through them.
它们不会触发碰撞 但会被渲染为游戏对象
They don't trigger collision, but they're rendered as game objects.
它们不是瓷砖网格的一部分
They're not part of the tile grid.
它们的处理方式不同于瓷砖
They don't get processed in the same way as tiles.
它们不是存储在y x中
They're not stored in the y, x.
这就是我们开始思考物体的有效方式
So that's effectively how we can start thinking about objects
以及如何赋予他们行为举止
and how to give them behavior.
作业的一部分将是添加一面旗帜
Part of the assignment is going to be adding a flag.
所以这面旗帜在精灵纸上
So this flag is in the sprite sheet.
所以你要做的是--
So what you'll do--
我会在这节课的最后谈到这一点
and I'll touch on this at the end of the lecture here.
我们就快到了
We're getting close to it.
这些钥匙实际上在右下角--
These keys here actually at the bottom right--
所以任务的一部分将是--
so part of the assignment will be to--
它实际上就在这里
it's actually right here.
所以我会很快地复习一下
So I'll go over it really quickly.
确保玩家总是在坚实的地面上开始
Ensure the player always starts above solid land.
在这种情况下 当詹姆斯跑到这里时 你跑了第一个例子
So in this case, when James came up here and ran, you ran the first example.
在我们第一次开发这个游戏的时候
The very first time that we spawned the game,
这就在球员在x1产生的地方产生了一个裂痕
it generated a chasm right where the player spawned at x1.
因此 如果发生这种情况 他就会坠落而死
And so he just falls to his death if that happens.
就在门口 有人有什么想法吗？
Just right off the gate, anybody have any ideas
至于我们可以做些什么来检查我们是否在坚实的陆地上
as to what we could do to check to see if we're at solid land,
假设玩家的默认开始时间是x1？
assuming that the player's default start is at x1?
观众：在那块瓷砖上 检查它是不是实心的
AUDIENCE: At that tile, check if it's solid.
如果不是 那么只需将它移到x上 直到它为真
If not, then just move it there over x until it's true.
科尔顿·奥格登：是的
COLTON OGDEN: Yeah.
我们可能想要做的是沿着柱子往下看
What we probably want to do is look all the way down the column,
因为我们从最高处开始
because we start towards the top.
如果我们发现下面没有瓷砖--这只是一个纯粹的裂缝--
If we find that there's no tiles down there-- it's just pure chasm--
我们可能想换掉这名球员
we probably want to shift the player.
然后随机的钥匙和锁--
And then random keys and locks--
让我打开LevelMaker 这样我们就可以看到您将与什么交互
let me open up LevelMaker so we can see what you'll be interacting with,
因为您实际上要做的大部分事情都是在LevelMaker中完成的
because most of what you'll be doing actually is in LevelMaker.
它做了很多我们以前用数学做的事情 随机的
It does a lot of what we did before with just math.random,
然后它会插入到物体中
and then it will insert into objects.
所以物体在这里是一张桌子
So objects is a table here.
它会根据某种逻辑插入一个游戏对象
It will insert a game object depending on some logic.
所以在这种情况下 如果我们要产生一根柱子
So in this case, if we're generating a pillar,
我们有机会在柱子上长出灌木丛
we have a chance to generate a bush on the pillar.
因此 如果math.dom(8)是1 那么在本例中 我们已经生成了一个柱
So if math.random(8) is 1, in this case, we're already generating a pillar.
所以我们有一个额外的机会 这是在机会之上
So we have an additional chance that's on top of the chance
以产生一根柱子--
to generated a pillar--
所以基本上 我认为在那个特定的迭代中有64%的几率
so basically, I think it's a 1 in 64 chance on that particular iteration
用灌木造一根柱子
to generate a pillar with a bush.
您只需将新的游戏对象添加到对象中
You just add a new game object to objects.
在本例中 这是游戏对象的构造函数
In this case, this is the constructor for a game object.
你给它一个x y 宽度 高度 然后是一个框架
You give it an x, y, width, height, and then a frame.
然后 该帧相对于与纹理匹配的任何四元表
And then the frame is relative to whatever quad table matches the texture
这里有一根线
string here.
所以灌木丛就是纹理 所以灌木丛中的任何四边形
So bushes is the texture, and so whatever quad in bushes
你想给它--
you want to give it--
在这种情况下 我们只是给了它一个随机的帧
in this case, we just gave it a random frame from that.
然后 许多相同的逻辑也适用于其他部分
And then a lot of the same logic applies to other parts.
这是我们在平地上生长灌木丛的另一个部分
This is another part where we generate bushes just on flat land.
我们有机会产生一个积木--
We have a chance to generate a block--
十分之一的几率这是一个跳跃障碍
1 in 10 chance this is a jump block.
所以这里我们有纹理 x y 宽度 高度 边框
So here we have texture, x, y, width, height, frame.
注意 我们有可碰撞的是真的 这是
Notice that we have collidable is true, and this
就是我们如何测试瓷砖是否可碰撞
is how we can test to see whether a tile is collidable or not.
Hit为FALSE 意味着我们还没有达到它
Hit is false, meaning that we haven't hit it yet.
如果我们击中了它 那么我们基本上执行这个代码--onCollide被调用
And if we have hit it, then we do this code basically-- onCollide gets called.
您可以看到在冲突代码中调用它的位置--
You can see where this gets called in the collision code for--
如果我们看球员的话
if we look in Player.
玩家有检查左碰撞 检查右碰撞
Player has check left collisions, check right collisions,
并检查对象碰撞
and check object collisions.
它没有向上和向下检查碰撞
It doesn't have check up and down collisions.
对于这两种情况都有一个角落的案例
There is a corner case for both of those such
这种逻辑必须被复制
that the logic had to be duplicated.
我忘记了确切的原因
I forget exactly why.
但你基本上得到了一个你要检查的对象的列表
But you basically get a list of objects that you check for.
哦 原因是当你得到
Oh, the reason why is because when you get
当你处于跳跃状态时碰撞的物体
the collided objects when you're in the jump state,
您可以触发onCollide函数
you trigger the onCollide function.
那么 让我们来看看PlayerJumpState
So let's go to PlayerJumpState.
如果我们处于跳跃状态 这基本上就是我们
If we're in the jump state, this is where we would basically
检查是否有任何物体与玩家发生碰撞
check to see if we've gotten any objects that collide with the player.
如果它是实心的 则调用其onCollide函数object.onCollide 然后
If it's solid, call its onCollide function, object.onCollide, and then
基本上 我们只传入对象本身
we just pass in the object itself, basically.
所以如果你回到LevelMaker 那就是
And so if you go back to LevelMaker, that's
在那里我们编写onCollide函数
where we write the onCollide function.
我们在此处的游戏对象中编写onCollide函数
We write the onCollide function within the game object here.
所以我们就给它一个OnCollide 记住
So we just give it an onCollide, remember,
因为函数是一等公民
because functions are first class citizens.
我们可以这样说 onCollide获取函数obj
We can just say onCollide gets function obj,
其中obj将成为这个对象
where obj is going to be this object.
如果它还没有被击中 五分之一的机会刷新宝石-
If it wasn't hit already, one in five chance to spawn a gem--
所以要创造一个宝石
so going to create a gem.
里面的东西都一样
It's got all the same stuff in it.
在这种情况下 它有自己的函数onConversion
In this case, it has its own function called onConsume.
onConclusion接受一个玩家和一个对象
onConsume takes a player and an object.
顺便说一下 这都是武断的
And then this is all arbitrary, by the way.
你可以创建任何你想要的功能
You can create whatever functions you want.
这些都是回调函数 有效的
These are callback functions, effectively.
我们只需要播放拾音器的声音 然后在分数上加100
We're just going to play the pickup sound and then add 100 to our score.
然后在这里 如果我们真的得到了一颗宝石
And then here, in the event that we did get a gem,
我们在0.1秒的时间内补间它
we tween it over the course of 0.1 seconds.
我们把它的y从下面的块到上面
We tween its y to be from below the block to up above,
所以它有一个向上的动画效果
so it has an upwards animation, effectively.
然后我们有另一个声音播放
And then we have another sound that plays.
但这就是我们生成游戏对象的有效方式
But that's effectively how we're spawning game objects.
游戏对象有纹理 x y 宽度 高度 然后
Game objects have textures, x, y, width, height, and then
你可以给他们回调函数
you can give them callback functions that you then
执行任何与你相关的事情
execute wherever it's relevant to you.
在这种情况下 你只需要担心onCollide
In this case, you'll only really need to worry about onCollide,
因为任务是创建随机密钥和锁
because the assignment is create random keys and locks.
它们必须是相同的颜色 但你可以随机选择它们
They have to be the same color, but you can choose them at random.
如果玩家碰到钥匙
If the player collides with the key, then he
可能会得到一些标志 比如key获得为true
should probably get some flag that's like key obtained is true
或者类似的东西
or something like that.
然后你去关卡中生成的区块
And then you go to the block that spawns in the level,
所以应该生成一个颜色相同块
so you should spawn a block with that same color.
然后在碰撞 你应该解锁它 所以摆脱块
And then on collide, you should unlock it, so get rid of the block
然后产生一个新的游戏对象--
and then spawn a new game object--
国旗
the flag.
然后这个标志将有自己的碰撞
And then that flag will have its own on collide.
当你撞到旗子时 重新开始
And when you collide with the flag, restart the level.
这实际上就是问题集的要点
And that's effectively the gist behind the problem set.
所以可能不需要...
So it probably shouldn't take--
我会说大概40或50行代码就可以了
I would say probably maybe 40 or 50 lines of code probably should do it.
观众：那个游戏物体--
AUDIENCE: That game object--
是在上课吗
was that a class?
这不是桌子
It's not a table.
那是什么？
What is that?
科尔顿·奥格登：这是一个类
COLTON OGDEN: It is a class.
有一个GameObject类
There's a GameObject class.
游戏对象基本上是--我意识到我没有太多地触及它
A game object is basically-- and I realize I didn't touch on it too much.
在这个发行版的上下文中 您几乎可以将其视为一个实体
In the context of this distro, you could almost think of it as an entity.
在这种情况下 我所做的是区分
In this case, what I've done is I've differentiated
在生物和非生物之间
between living things and non-living things
是实体还是游戏对象 这是一种半随意的区别
as being entities versus game objects, which is a semi-arbitrary distinction.
但对于这样一个小项目来说 这是有意义的
But for a small project like this, it makes sense.
对于大型项目 我可能会将所有内容都创建为一个实体
For a large project, I would probably create everything as an entity
然后给出不同类型的实体
and then give different kinds of entities
它们自己的行为和它们自己的组件
their own behavior and their own components,
有点像您处理实体组件系统的方式
sort of like how you do with an entity component system.
观众：在Lua中有两种创建类的方法吗
AUDIENCE: Are there two ways to create a class in Lua,
一个带大括号的和一个带正括号的？
one with the curly brackets and one with regular parentheses?
科尔顿·奥格登：事实上是有的
COLTON OGDEN: There is, actually.
所以问题是 在Lua中创建类的方法不止一种吗
So the question was, is there more than one way to create a class in Lua
无论是圆括号还是花括号？
whether it's parentheses or curly brackets?
是
Yes.
我想我从来没有真正谈过这个
I don't think I've ever actually talked about this.
让我们回到LevelMaker
Let's go back to LevelMaker.
如果您实例化一个类和该类
If you instantiate a class and that class
只接受一个表作为它的唯一参数 你可以直接传入这个
takes in just a table as its only argument, you can just pass in this.
这实际上就是参数表
This effectively is that argument table.
你不需要括号
You don't need parentheses.
它有效地做到了这一点--
It's effectively doing this--
同样的事情 只是你不需要括号
same thing, only you don't need the parentheses.
观众：然后那是一张被传进来的桌子？
AUDIENCE: And then that's a table that's being passed in?
科尔顿·奥格登：正确
COLTON OGDEN: Correct.
这只是实例化的另一种形式
It's just an alternative form of instantiation
关于那些只把表作为他们什么时候的论据的东西
on things that only take a table as their argument for when
它们被实例化
they get instantiated.
观众：那样的话你们只能有一张桌子吗？
AUDIENCE: And you can only have one table in that case?
科尔顿·奥格登：正确 是的
COLTON OGDEN: Correct, yes.
观众：创建一个新的班级不是更容易吗？
AUDIENCE: Wouldn't it be easier to create a new class which
会有自己的一组游戏对象 所以你
would have its own set of game objects so you
将创建一个GEM 它将是Helper Dot Gem 它
would create a gem which would be helper dot gem, which
会反过来创建一个游戏对象吗？
would in turn create a game object?
科尔顿·奥格登：你能再说一次吗？
COLTON OGDEN: Can you say that one more time?
观众：这很难解释
AUDIENCE: It's kind of hard to explain.
创建另一个类不是更容易吗？
Wouldn't it be easier to create another class which
会有你的宝石和所有东西 你的宝石在那个班级里
would have your gem and everything, and your gem in that class
会是一个游戏对象吗？
would be a game object?
但在这堂课上 当你想要宝石的时候
But in this class, when you wanted a gem,
你会说本地gem等同于helper类的点gem
you would say local gem equals helper class dot gem.
科尔顿·奥格登：问题是 不是吗？
COLTON OGDEN: The question was, wouldn't it
创建一个helper类来实例化gem会更容易吗？
be easier to create a helper class that would allow you to instantiate gems?
有可能
Possibly.
我想如果你把这个设计得更有力一点
I think if you were going to design this a little bit more robustly,
如果这是一场更大的比赛
and if this were going to be a larger game,
然后 您只需为块、宝石等创建一个子类
then you would just create a subclass for blocks, gems, et cetera.
缩小发行版中的文件数量并进行排序
To shrink the number of files that we had in the distro and to sort
将所有东西整合在一起 并将所有级别代码放在一起
of consolidate everything together and put all of the level code together
在其中一个地方 我决定只将GameObject创建为一个抽象类
in one spot, I decided to just create GameObject as an abstract class that
然后 您只需在实际的
you could then just create your own behavior for within the actual
构造函数--这是这里的这一位 这只是表格--
constructor-- which is this bit here, which is just the table--
然后允许您覆盖onCollide和onConsumer函数
and then allow you to override the onCollide and onConsume functions.
你实际上可以给它任何你想要的功能
You can actually give it whatever functions you want.
您可以给它指定一些任意命名的函数 然后稍后对其进行测试
You could give this some arbitrary named function and then test for it later.
这几乎就像是一种晦涩的继承方式
This is almost like an obscure way of inheritance.
但我认为 如果我设计这件事的目标是让它成为真正的
But I think if I were to engineer this with the goal of making it a really
在大型比赛中 我只会把它分成两类
large game, I would just subclass.
我会为GEM创建一个类 为BLOCK创建一个类 为布什创建一个类
I would just create a class for gem, a class for block, a class for bush,
等等 等等
et cetera, et cetera.
对于这个例子来说 这并不是严格必要的
It wasn't strictly necessary for this example,
所以我们最终把所有东西都保留了一点
so we ended up keeping everything a little bit
在某种意义上更抽象--更一般的目的
more abstract in a sense-- a little bit more general purpose.
但是 是的 你绝对可以为这些人创建类
But yeah, you could definitely create classes for those.
如果您处于实体组件系统中
And if you were in an entity component system,
你可以有一个可消耗的部件
you could have a consumable component.
然后 该消耗性组件将会
And then that consumable component would then
允许你给它一些影响玩家的行为 当
allow you to give it some sort of behavior that affects the player when
玩家消耗该物品
the player consumes that object.
在本例中 宝石是一种消耗品 因此您只需
In this case, a gem is a consumable, so you would just
给它一个具有宝石质地的可消耗成分
give it a consumable component with a texture of the gem
然后给它一个回调函数
and then give it a callback function that
只会增加玩家的分数
just increments the player's score.
你可以用10到15行代码来实现
You could probably put that in 10 or 15 lines of code.
很简单的
It would be pretty easy.
然后块将是一个产卵器组件
And then blocks would be a spawner component,
这样它们才有机会产卵
so they have a chance to spawn.
然后你会传入spawner组件一个gem
And then you would pass in that spawner component a gem maybe,
这样它就有机会将你放入产卵器的宝石产卵
so it would have a chance to spawn the gem that you passed into the spawner
然后是一个固体成分 这是固体
component-- and then also a solid component to say, oh, this is solid.
所以如果我撞到它 我应该会引发碰撞
So if I hit it, I should trigger a collision
却无法穿过它
and not be able to walk through it.
所以你只需要把这些组件叠加起来
So you just layer on these components.
我鼓励你们思考这种作曲方式
I would encourage you to think about this way of composing
你的对象有点 特别是当我们走向统一
your objects a little bit, particularly as we get towards Unity, which
很多人使用了这个概念
makes a lot of use of this concept.
简而言之 是的
In short, yes.
我想差不多就这些了
I think that's pretty much everything.
我先走了
Let me just go ahead.
我们快没时间了但我说了再说一次
We're running out of time here, but like I said, one more time--
确保播放器开始以上坚实的土地 随机颜色的关键和锁
make sure the player starts above solid land, random color key and lock,
然后确保当你拿到钥匙的时候 你可以打开锁
and then make sure that when you get the key, you can unlock the lock,
这就产生了目标
and that spawns the goal.
这些都是你可以添加到LevelMaker类中的
So this is all something you can just add to the LevelMaker class,
这一切都将与你的游戏水平的方式
and it will all work with your game level that way.
然后你触摸目标旗 然后重生的水平
And then you touch the goal flag, then respawn the level.
今天 我们来谈谈《超级马里奥兄弟》
So today, we talked about Super Mario Bros.
那个时代的另一款任天堂游戏
The other big Nintendo game of that era--
可以说是有史以来最伟大的电影之一--就是塞尔达
arguably one of the greatest of all time-- is Zelda.
所以我们将讨论一个非常简单的塞尔达传说游戏
So we'll be talking about a very simple Legend of Zelda game,
我们有一个随机的地牢可以去
where we just have a random dungeon that we can go through,
一个自上而下的视角 与简单的怪物战斗
a top down perspective, fight simple monsters,
开胸炸墙之类的
open chests, blow up walls-- that sort of thing.
我们将讨论触发器和事件
We'll talk about triggers and events.
然后我们再谈受伤的箱子 库存
And then we'll talk about hurt boxes, inventory,
一个非常简单的GUI 用于打开菜单
a very simple GUI for opening up a menu, and then world states
这样我们就能看到哪些门被炸开了
so that we can see which doors have been blasted open so that they
适当地渲染 诸如此类
render appropriately and whatnot.
马里奥就到此为止了
And that's it for Mario.
非常感谢您的光临
Thanks a lot for coming.
下次再见了
I'll see you guys next time.